<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Land-lords law a treatise very fit for the perusal of all gentlemen and others : being a collection of several cases in the law concerning leases, distresses, replevins, rescous, waste, and several other matters which often happen between land-lord and tenant, as appears in the contents of the several chapters / by G. Meriton ...</title>
            <author>Meriton, George, 1634-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12351142</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12351142</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 642:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Land-lords law a treatise very fit for the perusal of all gentlemen and others : being a collection of several cases in the law concerning leases, distresses, replevins, rescous, waste, and several other matters which often happen between land-lord and tenant, as appears in the contents of the several chapters / by G. Meriton ...</title>
                  <author>Meriton, George, 1634-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 171 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Twyford, Thomas Dring, and John Place,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An alphabetical table" [i.e. index]: prelim. p. [5]-[13].</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Landlord and tenant --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:1"/>
            <p>LAND-LORDS LAW: A <hi>Treatiſe</hi> very fit for the Peruſal of all Gentlemen and others.</p>
            <p>BEING A <hi>Collection</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Caſes</hi> in the Law concerning <hi>Leaſes, Diſtreſſes, Replevins, Reſcous, Waſte,</hi> and ſeveral other matters which often happen between <hi>Land-Lord</hi> and <hi>Tenant,</hi> as appears in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the ſeveral Chapters.</p>
            <p>By <hi>G. Meriton,</hi> Gent. <hi>olim Clericum Cliffordienſem.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hor.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>—Si quid noviſti rectius iſtis, Candidus imperti; ſi non, his utere me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Twyford, Thomas Dring,</hi> and <hi>John Place.</hi> 1665.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:2"/>
            <head>To All Gentlemen Land-Lords, and other knowing Perſons of this Kingdom.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving formerly had ſeveral Doubts and Quaere's in my minde, upon ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Caſes which oftentimes come in queſtion betwixt Land-Lords and their Tenants, and being deſirous to ſatisfie my ſelf in thoſe points; I thereupon made it my Study and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creation at ſome ſpare hours to ſearch and collect ſome choice Caſes, (out of the <hi>Reports</hi> and other Works of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Learned and Grave Judges, and other Sages of the Law) touching the <hi>Covenants, Conditions, Grants, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoes, Reſervations, Exceptions, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renders, Aſſignments,</hi> and many other things concerning <hi>Leaſes;</hi> as alſo
<pb facs="tcp:60010:3"/>
touching <hi>Diſtreſſes, Reſcous, Avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Replevins, Waſte,</hi> and other matters often coming in debate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Land-Lords and their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, as appears in the ſeveral Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters hereafter in this ſmall Treatiſe. Which little Manual at the firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking was intended onely for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate uſe, and a <hi>Vade mecum</hi> for my own Pocket; but having ſince com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated it to ſome ſpecial Friends and knowing Gentlemen, they have been very importunate with me for the publiſhing of it; at whoſe requeſts (they being my very intimate Friends and Acquaintance) I have now adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured this ſmall imperfect Treatiſe to the publick view. If it finde Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance it will be much Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your humble Servant, GEORGE MERITON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_cases">
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:3"/>
            <head>An Alphabetical Table of the Names of the Caſes vouched in this Book.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>A</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>AMphurſt and Palmer's Caſe, Paſc. 19 Jac. Rot. 2048. Hobart's Rep. f. 331.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Page</hi> 66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Amnor and Loddington's Caſe, M. 26 &amp; 27 Eliz. vouched in Cook's 1 part Inſt. f. 351. a.</cell>
                     <cell>79</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>B</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>BUtt's Caſe, 42 Eliz. in C. B. Cook's 7. lib. f. 23.</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Biſhop of Bath and Wells's Caſe, 3 Jac. in C. B. Co. 6. lib. fo. 34, &amp; 35.</cell>
                     <cell>2, &amp; 74</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Barker and Fleetwel's Caſe, 29 Eliz. in B. R. Godbolt's Rep. f. 69.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Beverley's Caſe, 24 Car. Clayton's Rep. p. 111. pl. 189.</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Browning's Caſe, Plo. Com. f. 136.</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Boroughs and Taylor's Caſe, Paſc. 38 El. in B. R. Goldsborough's Rep. f. 124. pl. 9.</cell>
                     <cell>49, &amp; 62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bredon's Caſe, M. 39 &amp; 40 Eliz. Co. 1. lib. f. 76.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60010:4"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Boraſton's Caſe, 29 Eliz. Co. 3. lib. f. 19.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bettiſworth's Caſe, 33 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 2. lib. f. 31.</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Barwick's Caſe, in the Exchequer, Co. 5. lib. f. 93.</cell>
                     <cell>71, &amp; 74</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Brudenell's Caſe, 34 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 5. l. f.</cell>
                     <cell>77, &amp; 83</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lewis Bowles's Caſe, 13 Jac. Co. 11. lib. f. 79.</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Berdſley and Pilkinton's Caſe, Goldsbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough's Rep. f. 100.</cell>
                     <cell>98</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bagſhaw and Goward's Caſe, Hil. 3 Jac. in B. R. Rot. 1070. Crook's Rep. 2 part, f. 147.</cell>
                     <cell>110</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bevil's Caſe, Mich. 27 and 28 Eliz. Co. 4. lib. f. 11.</cell>
                     <cell>111</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Beaumont's Caſe, 10 Jac. Co. 9. lib. f. 138.</cell>
                     <cell>147</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bingham's Caſe, Co. 2. lib. fo. 92.</cell>
                     <cell>151</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>C</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>COmpton and Allen's Caſe, Trin. 1649. Rot. 348. in B. R. Styles Rep. f. 162.</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cole and Taunton's Caſe, Hil. 36 Eliz. Rot. 376. Goldsborough's Rep. f. 184. pl. 122.</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Colthirſt's Caſe, Plo. Com. fo. 28. b.</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clun's Caſe, 11 Jac. in B. R. Co. 10. lib. fo. 227.</cell>
                     <cell>45, 46, and 48</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cibill and Hill's Caſe, M. 30 Eliz. in C. B. Leonard's Rep. f. 110.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cranley and Kingſwell's Caſe, Paſc. 15 Jac. Rot. 710. Hobart's Rep. fo. 207.</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:60010:4"/>
Cecil's Caſe, Dyer's Rep. 253.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clayton's Caſe, 37 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 5. lib. fo. 1.</cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Clifton's Caſe, 35 Eliz. Co. 5. lib. fo. 73.</cell>
                     <cell>149</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>D</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>DEan and Chapter of Windſor's Caſe, M. 44 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 5. lib. f. 24.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dumport's Caſe, Hil. 45 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 4. lib. f. 119.</cell>
                     <cell>20, 35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Darcy and Askwith's Caſe, Hil. 15 Jac. Hobart's Rep. f. 234.</cell>
                     <cell>138</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dean and Chapter of Worceſter's Caſe, 3 Jac. Co. 6. l. f. 37.</cell>
                     <cell>151</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>E</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ELlis and Chowne's Caſe, Hil. 44 Eliz. in C. B. Rot. 1459. vouched in Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 45.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>F</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>FArrington's Caſe, Dyer's Rep. f. 67.</cell>
                     <cell>26, 82<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fulmerſton's Caſe, Plo. Co. fo. 107. b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Foord's Caſe, 37 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 81.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sr William<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Foſter's Caſe, M. 6 Jac. Co. 8. l. f. 64.</cell>
                     <cell>123</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60010:5"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>G</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>GReen's Caſe, Anno 1650. Clayton's Rep. pa. 146. pl. 265.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gough's Caſe, 4 Mar. Dyer's Rep. 141.</cell>
                     <cell>53.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Goddard's Caſe, M. 34 Eliz. in C. B. Owen's Rep. f. 10.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sr. Rich. Grobham and Thornborough's Caſe, Hil. 10 Jac. Rot. 1793. Hobart's Rep. f. 82.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Green's Caſe, 18 Eliz. Leonard's Rep. f. 262.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Goddard's Caſe, 26 Eliz. Co. 2. l. fo. 5.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gomerſal and Wayt's Caſe, M. 8 Jac. in B. R. Crook's Rep. 2 part, fo. 255.</cell>
                     <cell>97</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>H</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>HArding's Caſe, M. 30 Eliz. in B. R. Godbolt's Rep. f. 139.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dame Hale's Caſe, Plo. Com. fo. 260. b.</cell>
                     <cell>33, 81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hill and Grange's Caſe, Plo. Com. fo. 171.</cell>
                     <cell>35, 63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Humble and Oliver's Caſe, M. 36 Eliz. in B. R. Popham's Rep. f. 55.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hare and Savil's Caſe, M. 7 Jac. in C. B. Brownloe's Rep. 2 part, fo. 273.</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hopkins and Morton's Caſe, vouched in Pennant's Caſe, Co. 3. lib. fo. 53.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Howe and Broome's Caſe, Hil. 43 Eliz. Goldsborough's Rep. f. 125. pl. 15.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Howel and Samback's Caſe, M. 13 Jac.
<pb facs="tcp:60010:5"/>
Rot. 2009. Hobart's Rep. f. 133.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hanſon and Norcliff's Caſe, Hil. 18 Jac. Rot. 2861. Hobart's Rep. f. 331.</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Harbin and Barton's Caſe, Goldsborough's Rep. f. 187. pl. 130.</cell>
                     <cell>81, 83.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Henſtead's Caſe, M. 36 &amp; 37 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 10.</cell>
                     <cell>84</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hunt and Downam's Caſe, Paſc. 16. Jac. in B. R. Crook's Rep. 2 part, fo. 478.</cell>
                     <cell>85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Harlackenden's Caſe, 31 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 4. lib. fo. 31.</cell>
                     <cell>92, 127, 128<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>K</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>KIdwell's Caſe, Plo. Com. 70.</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sr Henry Knivet and Pool's Caſe, Goldsborough's Rep. f. 143. pl. 60.</cell>
                     <cell>88</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>L</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>LEeds and Crompton's Caſe, M.</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Eliz. in C. B. vouced in Hughes's grand Abr. of the Law, 1 part, p. 428. c. 5.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lutterell's Caſe, 43 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 4. lib. fo. 86.</cell>
                     <cell>35, 91</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>London's Caſe, vouched in Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 47. b.</cell>
                     <cell>44<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>M</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>SIr Anthony Mayn's Caſe, 38 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 20.</cell>
                     <cell>12, 14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marrow and Turpin's Caſe, Paſc. 41 Eliz. in C. B. Rot. 2485.</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:60010:6"/>
March and Brace's Caſe, M. 11 Jac. in B. R. Bulſtrode's Rep. 2 part, 151.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Mountjoy's Caſe, M. 31 &amp; 32 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 5. lib. f. 3.</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Manley &amp; Jennings's Caſe, Paſc. 10 Jac. in C. B. Brownloe's Rep. 2 part, f. 176.</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>March and Curtie's Caſe, 40 Eliz. in C. B. Rot. 1302. vouched in Pennant's Caſe, Co. 3. l. f. 65.</cell>
                     <cell>64, 65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mallery's Caſe, 43 El. Co. 5. l. f. 111.</cell>
                     <cell>77</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Manning's Caſe, 7 Jac. Co. 8. lib. fo. 94.</cell>
                     <cell>79</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>More and Conham's Caſe, M. 7 Jac. in C. B. Owen's Rep. f. 123.</cell>
                     <cell>110</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>N</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>NIchols Caſe, Plo. Com. fo. 487.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>O</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>OVerton and Siddal's Caſe, 37 Eliz. in B. R. vouched in Co. 3. l in Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's Caſe there, f.</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Oland's Caſe, 44 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 5. l. f. 116.</cell>
                     <cell>90</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Osborn and Rider's Caſe, Hil. 13 Jac. in B. R. Crook's Rep. 2 part, 135.</cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ognell's Caſe, 29 Eliz. Co. 4. lib. fo. 49.</cell>
                     <cell>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>P</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>PEnnant's Caſe, 38 Eliz. Co. 3. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 52, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60010:6"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Page and Parr's Caſe, in B. R. Styles Rep. fo. 243.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Paradine and Joxe's Caſe, M. 23 Car. in B. R. Styles Rep. f. 47 &amp; 48.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pepall and Hammington's Caſe, 17 Eliz. in B. R. Popham's Rep. 117, &amp; 118.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Partridge and Naylor's Caſe, Goldsbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough's Rep. f. 145. pl. 62.</cell>
                     <cell>98</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Paget's Caſe, 35 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 76.</cell>
                     <cell>151</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>R</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>REctor of Cheddington's Caſe, 40 El. Co. 1. l. 155, &amp; 156.</cell>
                     <cell>2, 68, 73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Revel and Hart's Caſe, Goldsborough's Rep. f. 138. pl. 44.</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Remmington and Kingerbie's Caſe, 18 Car. in B. R. Styles Rep. f. 4.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>SPencer's Caſe, Paſc. 29 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 5. l. fo. 16, &amp; 17.</cell>
                     <cell>13, 35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sr John Spencer and Sr Jo. Poyne's Caſe, Tr. 5 Jac. in B. R. Godbolt's Rep. fo. 154.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Say and Fuller's Caſe, Plo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Com. f. 272. b.</cell>
                     <cell>74</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Savin's Caſe, 3 Jac. in C. B. Co. 5. lib. f. 123.</cell>
                     <cell>77</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sayer and Hardye's Caſe, Goldsborough's Rep. f. 179. pl. 112.</cell>
                     <cell>82</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Saunder's Caſe, 41 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 5. l. fo. 12.</cell>
                     <cell>139</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:60010:7"/>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>T</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>TReport's Caſe, M. 37 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 6. l. f. 15.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Thyn and Cholmley's Caſe, Tr. 36 Eliz. Goldsborough's Rep. fo. 186. pl. 129.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tooker's Caſe, 43 Eliz. Co. 2. lib. fo. 39.</cell>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tintnye and James's Caſe, Tr. 15 Car. in B. R. Winche's Rep. fo. 30, &amp; 31.</cell>
                     <cell>122</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>U</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>UNgle and Glover's Caſe, 36 Eliz. vouched in Walker's Caſe, Co. 3. lib. fo.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>W</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>WRoth and the Counteſs of Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex's Caſe, P. 28 Eliz. Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard's Rep. 1 part, 131.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Wotton and Edwin's Caſe, 5 Jac. in B. R. vouched in Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 47. a.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Watt and Maidwell's Caſe, 3 Car. Rot. 1302. in B. R. Hutton's Rep. 104.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Wade's Caſe, 43 Eliz. in C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 111.</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lord Willoughbie's Caſe, Dyer's Rep. fo. 80.</cell>
                     <cell>68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60010:7"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Walker's Caſe, 29 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 3. l. f. 22.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 41, 147</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Walgrave and Somerſet's Caſe, M. 29, 30 Eliz. Goldsborough's Rep. fo. 72. pl. 17.</cell>
                     <cell>141</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:8"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:8"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Chapters.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Leaſes: Who may make them, and for what Term; and Who are called Tenants for Life, Tenants for term of Years, at Will &amp; Sufferance.</cell>
                     <cell>Page 1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Covenants, Conditions, Grants, Proviſo's, Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Exceptions, Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Aſsignments, &amp;c. of Leaſes.</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Payments, Rents, Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Confirmations, Extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhments, Demands, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entries, Limitations, &amp;c. of Leaſes.</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60010:9"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Dates, Commencements, Continuance, and Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Leaſes.</cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of Corn ſown where the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is outed, or the Term determines before it be ripe, who ſhall have it: and alſo of Eſtovers, and Trees blown down, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>87</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of Diſtreſſes. Of what things a Diſtreſs may be taken, and how it muſt be uſed, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>94</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Who may take a Diſtreſs, and for what cauſe, and when, and where.</cell>
                     <cell>102</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Of Reſcous, where it ſhall be lawful.</cell>
                     <cell>110</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:60010:9"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of Replevins, when and where to be ſued out.</cell>
                     <cell>114</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of Avowries, a word or two briefly concerning the ſame.</cell>
                     <cell>121</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> Of Waſte: What ſhall be Waſte in Houſes, Gardens, Woods, Paſtures, &amp;c. and what not.</cell>
                     <cell>126</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Who are puniſhable in Waſte, and for what Waſte, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>140</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> An Abridgment of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the 43 <hi>Elizab.</hi> and the 15 of <hi>Car.</hi> 2. about the unlawful cutting, ſtealing or ſpoiling of Wood, &amp;c. neceſſary for all Gentlemen to know.</cell>
                     <cell>164</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60010:10"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60010:10"/>
            <head>Land-Lords Law.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of Leaſes: Who may make them, and for what Term; and Who are called Tenants for Life, Tenants for term of Years, at Will and Sufferance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEASE is derived from <note place="margin">Bract. lib. 4. fo. 220. Fleta lib. 3. cha. 12. Coo. on Lit. f. 43. b.</note> 
                  <hi>Leapum</hi> or <hi>Leaſum,</hi> for that the Leſſee cometh in by Lawful means; and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere</hi> is in <hi>French Laiſſer,</hi> to depart with or forgoe.</p>
               <p>In every Leaſe there muſt be <note place="margin">Terms of the Law. verb. <hi>Leſſer</hi> and <hi>Leſſee.</hi>
                  </note> Leſſor, and Leſſee: he which lets the Land is called the Leſſor; and he which farms it is called the Leſſee.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe for Years of Lands
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60010:11"/>
and Tenements, is good as well without Deed as with Deed; but of a Common or Rent, &amp;c. it is not good without Deed.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe for Years be made <note place="margin">42 Eliz. in C. B. Butts Caſe. Co. 7. par. f. 23.</note> reſerving Rent, it muſt be of Lands and Tenements, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Leſſor may have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort to diſtrain; and therefore <note place="margin">30 Aſſ. p. 5. 12 Aſſ. 20. 20 E. 4. 10. Co. 1 par. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. f. 47. a.</note> a Rent cannot be reſerved by a common perſon out of any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal Inheritance, as Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowſons, Commons, Offices, Corrody, Mulcture of a Mill, Tithes, Fairs, Markets, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Franchiſes, &amp;c. But if the Leaſe be made by Deed in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, one may have an Action of Debt by way of Contract, but diſtrain one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not: but if any Rent be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in ſuch Caſes upon a Leaſe for Life, it is utterly void. <note place="margin">3 Jac. in C. B. Bp of Bath's Caſe. Co. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> par. f. 34, 35 40 Eliz. Rector of Chedington's Caſe. Co. 1 par. f. 155, 156. Bract. l. 2. c. 9. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 45. b.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Every Leaſe for years muſt be for a time certain, and ought to expreſs the Term, and when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60010:11"/>
it ſhould begin, and when it ſhould end. And yet there may be a certainty in an uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty ſometimes; for the Rule is, <hi>Id certum eſt, quod certum reddi poteſt:</hi> therefore look in the 4 Chapter, and you will finde ſome pretty Caſes there about this Rule.</p>
               <p>If a man have a Leaſe of <note place="margin">32 lib. Aſſ. 6.</note> Lands for 500 years, it is but a Chattel, and falls to his Executors or Adminiſtrators after his death, if he do not otherwiſe diſpoſe of it in his life-time.</p>
               <p>Every one ſeiſed of an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <note place="margin">Cowell Inſt. p. 189.</note> pure Eſtate in Fee-ſimple, may make a Leaſe of his Lands for as long a time as he pleaſeth; and ſo might Biſhops, &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were reſtrained by Statute. See 32 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 28. 13 <hi>El.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Coo. 1 par. of Inſt. f. 44. a. b. Noye's Maximes, p. 69. Bro. Leaſe 47. 32 H. 8. c. 28. Vide Herne's Law of Conve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 66, 67, &amp; 68.</note> 
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 10. 18 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 6.1 <hi>Jac. c.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Tenant in Tail, being of full age, by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Indenture in writing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60010:12"/>
may make a Leaſe of ſuch Lands and Inheritances as have been formerly letten to Farm for the ſpace of 20 years next before the Leaſe made; or if it be but letten 11 years at one or ſeveral times within thoſe 20, it is ſufficient, reſerving the old Rent or more; without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of Waſte muſt not be in it, and it muſt commence from the day of the making or from the making: and if there be an old Leaſe in being, it muſt be either ſurrendered, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired or ended within one year after the making of the new one, or elſe it is not good; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the Caſe of a Biſhop, which you will find afterwards. And if the Leaſe be thus made, it binds the Iſſue of Tenant in Tail, if he die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Term be out: but if he die without Iſſue, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor may avoid the Leaſe by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60010:12"/>
Entrie; and ſo may he in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder; and though he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Rent, yet it ſhall not affirm the Leaſe.</p>
               <p>The Husband ſeiſed in Fee-ſimple <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 44. Cowell's Inſt. p. 189 Noye's Maximes, p. 69.</note> or Fee-Tail in right of his Wife may make ſuch a Leaſe of his Wife's Land, by Indenture in writing, in the name of the Husband and Wife, and ſhe to ſeal thereunto; and the Rent muſt be reſerved to the Husband and his Wife, and to the Heirs of the Wife, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her Eſtate of Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance<hi>:</hi> and this ſhall binde her and her Heirs after his death.</p>
               <p>Biſhops, Deans and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 44. a. Cowel's Inſt. p. 189. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Law, p. 29.</note> &amp;c. ſeiſed of any Eſtate in Fee in right of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, obſerving the Rules afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, may make Leaſes: and ſo may Maſters and Fellows of Colleges, and Wardens of Hoſpitals, if their private Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60010:13"/>
will permit them.</p>
               <p>But note well, that Tenant <note place="margin">Co. ubi ſuprá. 32 H. 8. cap. 28.</note> in Tail and the perſons before named, though they do obſerve theſe Rules, yet they cannot let for any longer term then Three Lives, or 21 years, but for what term they will under.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Tail or any of the aforeſaid perſons obſerve <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 45. a.</note> not theſe Rules in their Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet notwithſtanding the Leaſes ſhall be good againſt them for their Lives.</p>
               <p>And if a Leaſe be made by a Biſhop for 21 years, according <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 45. a. Paſc. 28 El. in B. R. The Counteſs of Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex's Caſe. Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard's Rep. 1 par. 131. Parſons Law p. 27, 28. Vide Hern's Law of Conv. p. 69, 70.</note> to the Rules aforeſaid, which is ſpent within 3 years or more, now if the Biſhop make a new Leaſe to another for 21 years, to commence from the making, which is confirmed by the Dean and Chapter, this is a good Leaſe, and the ſecond Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee may enter when the firſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60010:13"/>
Leaſe is out, and hold for the Remainder of his term of 21 years then to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Demiſe, Grant, Betake to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 45. b. Bro. Leaſes 60. 37 H. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Farm-let,</hi> and whatſoever words amount to a Grant, may ſerve to make a Leaſe.</p>
               <p>Generally now every Leſſee <note place="margin">Terms de Ley, verb. <hi>Farm.</hi>
                  </note> for Life, Years, or at Will, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be of never ſo ſmall a Cottage or houſe, is called a Farmor or Fermor, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes he poſſeſſeth are called a Farm or Ferm.</p>
               <p>But formerly the chief Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuage <note place="margin">ibid.</note> in a Village or Town, whereunto belonged great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnes of all ſorts, which were uſed to be let for term of Life, Years, or at Will, was called a Farm or Ferm.</p>
               <p>They are called Farms or Ferms of the <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormion,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">ibid.</note> which ſignifies to feed or yield Victuals; for in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time their Reſervations
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60010:14"/>
were for the moſt part in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, until at the laſt, and that chiefly in the time of K. <hi>H.</hi> 1. by agreement, the Reſervation of Victuals was turned into Money, and ſo hitherto hath continued amongſt moſt men.</p>
               <p>Under the name of Lands are comprehended not onely Gardens, Meadows, Paſtures, Rivers, Woods, Moors, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Mariſhes, Furzes and Heath; but alſo Meſuages, Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Tofts, Mills, Caſtles, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor ſeal the Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 57. Finch, l. 2. cap. 2. p. 109.</note> and not the Leſſee, yet it is as good againſt the Leſſor as if both had ſealed.</p>
               <p>And if at any time there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 57. Lit. 88. 14 Eliz. Finch, l. 2. c. 2. p. 109.</note> any variance between the Indentures, it ſhall be taken as the Deed of the Leſſor is, and the other ſhall be intended onely the miſpriſion of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for the Leſſor's is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60010:14"/>
Deed, and the other but onely a Counterpane.</p>
               <p>Now we have ſpoken brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſomething concerning Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and who may make them, we ſhall next ſpeak ſomething of the ſeveral ſorts of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants mentioned in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and ſo conclude this Chapter.</p>
               <p>Tenant for Life is he who <note place="margin">Lit. Tenures, lib. 1. c. 6. Noye's Maxims, p. 30.</note> hath Lands or Tenements for his own or another mans Life; and this Tenant hath a Free-hold, but none other of leſſer Eſtate hath a Free-hold.</p>
               <p>If a man be Tenant for term <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fo. 42<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a.</note> of his own Life, he hath an higher Eſtate then he that is Tenant for another mans Life.</p>
               <p>Tenant for term of Years <note place="margin">Lit. Tenures, l. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Co. 1 par. Inſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 43. b. 44. a.</note> is, where a man letteth Lands of Tenements to another for a certain term of Years, as it is agreed between them; and when the Leſſee entereth, he is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60010:15"/>
then Tenant for term of years and if the Leſſor reſerve to him a Rent, he may either diſtrain on the premiſſes, or have an Action of Debt, if the Rent be arrear.</p>
               <p>There needs no Livery and <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8. a.</note> Seiſin to be given upon a Leaſe for Years, but the Leſſee may enter when he will; but a Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee for Life muſt have Livery, or elſe no Free-hold paſſeth.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roll <note place="margin">Lit. Tenures, l. 1. Finch, l. 2. cap. 2. p. 109. 38 H. 8. Br. Eſtoppel 8.</note> to another, it behoves that he be ſeiſed of the Lands or premiſſes at the time of the Leaſe made; for elſe the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee may plead that the Leſſor had nothing in the premiſſes at the time of the Leaſe made, and then he is barred of his Action: but if it be by Indenture in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, then the Leſſee cannot plead this Plea.</p>
               <p>Tenant at Will is, where <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 55. a. Fleta, l. 3. c. 15.</note> Lands or Tenements are let by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60010:15"/>
one man to another, to have and hold to him at the Will of the Leſſor: now when the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee enters, he is Tenant at Will, and the Leſſor may put him out when he pleaſes.</p>
               <p>But if a man let Lands to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <note place="margin">Coo. ib.</note> by Leaſe, to hold the ſame during the Will of the Leſſee, in this caſe the Law intends it to be at the Will of the Leſſor alſo, and he may put him out when he pleaſes. The ſame Law is if it be at the Will of the Leſſor, it is intended at the Leſſee's Will alſo, for the Leſſor cannot force him to ſtay longer then he pleaſes.</p>
               <p>Tenant at ſufferance is he <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. b. Brac. lib. 4. f. 318. 21 H. 6. f. 42. Kitchin, f. 238. a. 4 E. 3. 35. 24 E. 3.24. F. N. B. 201. D. Plow. Com. 138.</note> who comes in by lawful Leaſe, and keepeth poſſeſſion after his Leaſe is out, and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully holdeth over. <hi>Finch lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. As Tenant for Life of <hi>I. S.</hi> who holdeth over after the death of the ſaid <hi>I. S.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:60010:16"/>
The Leſſor cannot have an <note place="margin">Coo. ubi ſuprá.</note> Action of Treſpaſs againſt ſuch Tenant before his Entry into the Premiſſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Of the Covenants, Conditions, Grants, Proviſo's, Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Exceptions, Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Aſsignments,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>of Leaſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the Leſſor Covenant to <note place="margin">38 Eliz. Sir An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony Mayn's Caſe. Co. 5 par. f. 20. Noy's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximes, p. 13. Hughes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> grand Abr. 1 par. p. 487. c. 16.</note> make a new Leaſe upon Surrender of the old Leaſe, and afterwards he makes a Leaſe by Fine for more years to a Stranger, here the Covenant is broken, although the Leſſee did not Surrender, the which by the words ought to be the firſt Act; for that the Leſſor did diſable himſelf either to take
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60010:16"/>
the Surrender, or make the new Leaſe.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe for <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 17. &amp; 50. Dr. &amp; Stud. lib. 1. ca. 24.</note> Years, and the Leſſee covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and granteth to pay to the Leſſor, his Heirs and Aſſigns, yearly during, &amp;c. 10 pound; here if the Leſſor die, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors ſhall have the Rent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear.</p>
               <p>If a man covenant and grant <note place="margin">37 H. 8. Bro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaſes 60. Kit. Court-Leet, p. 235. b.</note> to <hi>R. A.</hi> that he ſhall have ten Acres of Land in <hi>C.</hi> for years, this is a good Leaſe, for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsit</hi> is of ſuch force as <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Leſſee covenant for <note place="margin">Paſch. 25 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 5 par. f. 16, 17. Spencer's Caſe. M. 29 Eliz. in B. R. Barker and Fleetwell's Caſe. Godbolt's Rep. fo. 69, 70. Vide Hern's Law of Conv. p. 107, 108, &amp; 109.</note> him and his Aſſigns, to build a Brick-wall or an Houſe upon the Leſſor's Land, or pay a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateral Summe of money to the Leſſor, and after the Leſſee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth over his Term; in this caſe the Aſſign ſhall not be bound by this Covenant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the things were onely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60010:17"/>
Collateral, and were not <hi>in eſſe,</hi> nor parcel of the Demiſe, at the time of the Leaſe made.</p>
               <p>If there be a Covenant in a <note place="margin">38 Eli. Co. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> par. f. 64. Pennant's Caſe. Cowell's Inſt. p. 193. Dyer f. 51.</note> Leaſe, that if the Rent be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde for ſuch a time, then the Leaſe to be void; here no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of the Rent after ſuch failure will make the Leaſe good.</p>
               <p>If a man let a Houſe and <note place="margin">Trin. 1649. Rot. 348. in B. R. Compton and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len's Caſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Styles 162. F. N. B. fo. 145. K. Noye's Max. p. 16. 40 E. 3. 5. Finch, p. 64. 38 Eliz. Sir Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Mayn's Caſe. Co. 5 par. l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 20.</note> Lands for years, and the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee covenanteth to uphold the Houſes, and to leave the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Lands in as good a plight and eſtate as he found them; in this caſe, if the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be blown down by Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt or fired by accident, or otherwiſe deſtroyed, if the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee do not repair and build them again, and leave them as good as he found them, the Leſſor may bring an Action of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant againſt him at the end of his term: but if he maketh
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60010:17"/>
Waſt in the cutting of Timber, the Leſſor may have an Action of Covenant before the end of the Term for that.</p>
               <p>And if the Leſſee for years <note place="margin">Mich. 44 Eliz. in B. R. Dean and Chapter of Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor's Ca. Co. 5 par. f. 24. Hughes's grand Abr. 1 par. p. 492. c. 19.</note> covenant and grant for him and his Executors with the Leſſor, to repair the Houſes as often as need requires, and after the Leſſee aſſigns over his term, and the Aſſignee ſuffers the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to decay; in this Caſe an Action of Covenant lies againſt the Aſſignee, although he be not named in the Covenant.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor covenant with <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 41. B. Dyer, f. 19.</note> the Leſſee, that he ſhall have ſufficient Hedge-bote by the Aſſignment of him or his Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff; here he may not take it without Aſſignment, <hi>Quia modus &amp; Conventio vincunt Legem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man take a Leaſe by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture <note place="margin">Perkins Tit. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</hi> 738. M. 1649. B R. Styles prac. Regiſt. p. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of a ruinous Houſe, or that wanteth Reparations, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60010:18"/>
do Covenant in the Leaſe to leave the Houſe at the end of the term in good Repair; here he is bound to leave it in good Repair whatſoever happen, by the Rule aforeſaid: but if he do not covenant to doe it, he is not bound by Law in ſuch caſe to doe it.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe for Years be made <note place="margin">Paſc. 14 H. 8. 32. Perkins 738. 40 E. 3. 6. Hughes's gr. Abridgment, p. 499. c. 2. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips's Principles of Law, p. 2.</note> of a Wood by Deed indented, and it is there covenanted that the Leſſee ſhall leave the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor's Wood in as good plight as it was at the time of the Leaſe made, and during the term the Wood is deſtroyed by a ſudden Tempeſt; in this caſe the Leſſor can have no Action of Covenant againſt the Leſſee, for the non-performance of this Covenant, for it is not poſſible for him to perform the ſame, and <hi>Lex non cogit Impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">22 H <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. See Goldsborough's<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 16. in the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made for Years
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60010:18"/>
rendring Rent, and the Leſſee is bound to perform all Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and Agreements, if he do not pay the Rent the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is forfeited; for the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Rent is an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>If a man be bound in an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 47.</note> to repair the Houſes of the Obligee as often as need ſhall require during ſuch a time, and after the Houſes need Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations; in this caſe, though the Obligor knoweth not that they need Reparations, yet he is bound to take notice at his peril, for Ignorance here excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not.</p>
               <p>But if the Condition had <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid.</note> been to repair ſuch Houſes as the Obligee ſhould aſſign, and after he aſſigneth, &amp;c. but the Obligor hath no notice of it; here the ignorance ſhall excuſe him, for the Obligee ought to give him notice: but if the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60010:19"/>
had been appointed to a Stranger, there the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor muſt have taken notice at his peril.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe for Years be made <note place="margin">Lit. 166. 26 H. 8. 3. Finch, lib. 2. c. 3. p. 115.</note> with Warranty, this ſounds not in the nature of a Warranty, but of a Covenant, becauſe it is but a Chattel; and if the Leſſee be ouſted, yet he may have an Action of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>If I be ſeiſed of 10 Acres <note place="margin">Paſch. 9 E. 4. 1. P. 24 E. 4. 34. P. 45 E. 3. 3. M. 44 E. 3.37. Perkins, 825.</note> of Land, and leaſe the ſame to a Stranger for Life or Years, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving 10<hi rend="sup">s</hi> Rent to me, &amp;c. payable at the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and the Leſſee doth bind himſelf to me in a bond of 100 pound, to pay the Rent reſerved upon the Leaſe juſtly according to Law; if before any day of payment I do put the Leſſee out of part of the Land, and he doth occupy the reſidue for the whole term, and will not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60010:19"/>
pay any Rent, yet the Bond is not forfeited; for by the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of the Leſſee of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Land the whole Rent is in ſuſpence: but if one <note place="margin">in B. R. Page and Par's Caſe. Styles Rep. 243.</note> day of payment be incurred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ouſter, then he muſt pay the Rent, or elſe the Bond is forfeited.</p>
               <p>If a Stranger who hath not <note place="margin">22 H 6. ac. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, 826. See Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radine &amp; Joxe's Caſe. M. 23 Car. in B. R. Styles Rep. f. 47, 48.</note> any right doth put out the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee for years of the ſame Land before any day of payment, and keep poſſeſſion thereof un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the day of payment be paſt, yet the Leſſee ought to pay me the Rent at the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ought to be pay'd, or otherwiſe he forfeits his Bond.</p>
               <p>If three Copartners be ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">P. 9 F. 4.1. M. 12 H. 8. 3. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</note> of a Mannor, and one of them in her own name, and without the agreement of the other two, doth leaſe the whole Mannor unto <hi>I. S.</hi> for 4 years, yielding 5 pound yearly at the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60010:20"/>
Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> unto the Leſſor and her Heirs, and <hi>I. S.</hi> doth bind himſelf in 40 pound unto his Leſſor to pay the Rent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, &amp;c. and before any day of payment the other two Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partners which did not conſent to the Leaſe do put the Leſſee out of the whole Mannor, and keep the poſſeſſion until the day of payment of the Rent be incurred; yet it behoveth the Leſſee to pay the Third part of the Rent reſerved to his Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, otherwiſe he forfeits his Bond: for the two Copartners who put him out have no Right but to two parts of the Mannor.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to three <note place="margin">28 Eliz. Lord Stafford's Caſe. 28 Eliz. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. B. Leeds and Crompton's Caſe. Hughes's gr. Abr. 1 par. p. 428.4 &amp; 5 P. &amp; M. Dyer 152. Vid. Co. 4 par. Dumpor's Caſe. 45 Eliz. in B. R.</note> upon Condition that they nor any of them ſhould aliene with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out licence, if the Leſſor give leave to one of them to aliene, now the other two may aliene without licence; for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60010:20"/>
being determined to one is determined to all.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor do enter for <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, pa. 72.</note> Condition broken, or the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee do ſurrender, or the Term end; yet the Leſſor may have an Action of Debt for the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rearages.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made upon <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. lib. 2. c. 35. M. 31 H 8. Dyer, f. 45. Co. l. 8. f. 90. b. 7 E. 4. 13. &amp; Philips's Pr. of Law, p. 14.</note> Condition that the Leſſee ſhall not aliene to <hi>A;</hi> if the Leſſee aliene to <hi>B,</hi> and he aliene to <hi>A,</hi> the Condition is not broken; for a Condition that goes to the breaking of an Eſtate ſhall be taken ſtrictly.</p>
               <p>If a man ſeiſed of Lands in <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. lib. 3. cap. 5. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 216. a. b. 217. a. b. Vide Lord Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford's Caſe. Co. 8 part, f. 73. Vide Herne's Law of Conveiance, p. 48. &amp; ſee Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chols Caſe. Pl. Com. f. 487. &amp; Kitchin, f. 219. a.</note> Fee leaſe the ſame to a Stranger by Indenture for five years, upon Condition that if the Leſſee pay to the Leſſor five pound within the two firſt years, that then he ſhall have Fee in the ſame Land; in this caſe if he pay the mony, he hath a good Eſtate in Fee, if Livery
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60010:21"/>
and Seiſin were made according to the Deed.</p>
               <p>But if a man ſeiſed of Land in Fee leaſe the ſame to a Stranger <note place="margin">Perkins 708. Vid. 9 H. 6.29.</note> for years, upon condition that if the Leſſee be ouſted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the term by his Leſſor, that then he ſhall have Fee; here if the Leſſee be ouſted by a Stranger without the Leſſor's aſſent, he ſhall not have Fee.</p>
               <p>If a man ſeiſed of Lands in Fee leaſeth the ſame to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <note place="margin">Perkins 710.</note> by Indenture, yielding 5 pound by the year, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture is, that if the Leſſee will hold over 10 years to him and his heirs, that he ſhall then pay 20 pound by the year, and Livery and Seiſin is made to the Leſſee accordingly; in this caſe for the Rent behind within the 10 years the Leſſor ſhall have an Action of Debt, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the Free-hold and the Fee are not in the Leſſee before the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60010:21"/>
10 years ended: but if when the ten years be paſt and ended the Leſſee doth continue the poſſeſſion of the ſame Land, and doth occupie the Land by force of the Indenture, then he hath Fee, and ſhall pay the 20 pound as a Rent ſect. But if a <note place="margin">M. 40 E. 3.27. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, 711. Coo. 1 par. Inſt. f. 218. b.</note> man ſeiſed of Land doth leaſe the ſame Land for Life, yielding unto him a Roſe for the firſt ſix years, and if he will hold the Land over the ſix years, that he ſhall pay 3 Marks by the year; in this caſe the Leſſee hath the Free-hold preſently.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe for Life or Years be <note place="margin">4 H. 7.4.8 E. 4. 13. P. 2 E. 4. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Perkins, 725, &amp; 723 Vide Herne's Law of Conv. p. 115.</note> made upon Condition, that if the Leſſee kill <hi>I. S.</hi> within the term, that then he ſhall have and hold the Land leaſed unto himſelf and his Heirs for ever; now if he kill <hi>I. S.</hi> within the term, yet his Eſtate is not inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thereby, becauſe the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is againſt Law, &amp; the Eſtate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60010:22"/>
doth begin to be inlarged upon the performance of the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet the Leaſe is good, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame doth not begin by the Condition.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made for Years <note place="margin">Perkins, 729, 730.</note> upon Condition, that if the Leſſor do aliene the Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on within the term, then the Leſſee ſhall have Fee, and the Leſſor doth aliene the Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Fee by Fine to a Stranger; now in this caſe the Leſſee ſhall not have Fee, for the Free-hold and the Fee are lawfully in the Conuſee before the Leſſee can take it by Condition: but if the Leſſor had granted by Deed onely to a Stranger, then the Leſſee ſhould have had Fee by the Condition; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe the Reverſion is not in the Grantee before At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tornment.</p>
               <p>If a man have a Leaſe for <note place="margin">Perkins, 833. Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Vide 21 H. 7.18. a. &amp; Co. 1 part of Inſtit. f. 214. b.</note>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:60010:22"/>
Years, and demiſe or grant the ſame upon Condition, &amp;c. and die; his Executors or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators ſhall enter for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition broken, for they are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie in right, and repreſent the perſon of the dead.</p>
               <p>All Grantees of Reverſions may enter upon Farmers for <note place="margin">32 H. 8. c. 34. Finch, l. 2. c. 1. pa. 107. Herne's Law of Convey. p. 31.</note> any Forfeiture or Condition, and have like advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them (by Action one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) for any other Covenants, Conditions or Agreements contained in the Indentures of their Leaſe, as the Leſſors, their Heirs or Aſſigns might; and the like for the Leſſees againſt the Grantees of the Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (Recovery in value onely excepted.)</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe for <note place="margin">Lit. l. 3. c. 8. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 292 b. 45 E. 3.8. 17 H. 6.26. Cowel's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. p. 193. Noye's Maximes, p. 77.</note> Years upon Condition that the Rent ſhall be paid at <hi>Michael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> and in the mean time give a general Releaſe to the Leſſee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60010:23"/>
of all Actions and Demands; yet this doth not remit the Rent, but the Leſſor may ſue for it: and the Reaſon of this is, becauſe it was neither <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum</hi> nor <hi>Solvendum</hi> at the time of the Releaſe made; and it is a thing not merely in Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe it may be granted over.</p>
               <p>If two take a Leaſe joyntly for Years with Condition, that <note place="margin">Vid. 3 F. 6. Dyer 67. Farrington's Caſe. Cowel's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. 199.</note> if the Leſſees die before the term ended the Leaſe ſhall be void; now the Leſſees make diviſion, and one of them alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nateth his part, and dies; in this caſe the Leſſor cannot reaſſume the part of him that died, but the Alienee ſhall have it du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of him that ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made for Years <note place="margin">Hil. 36 Eliz. Rot. 376. Cole and Taunton's Caſe. Goldsb. p. 184. pl. 122. Vid. the Caſe 31 H. 8.45.</note> upon Condition, that if the Leſſee demiſe the premiſſes or any part thereof other then for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60010:23"/>
a year to any perſon or perſons, then the Leſſor and his Heirs may re-enter; the Leſſee after deviſes it to his Son by his Will; this is a breach of the Condition.</p>
               <p>If a man of his mere motion <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. lib. 2. cap. 20. fo. 93. a.</note> enfeoffe <hi>H.</hi> by Indenture upon Condition that he ſhall yearly pay to <hi>I. S.</hi> out of the Lands a certain Rent, and if he fail in payment, that it ſhall then be lawful to the ſaid <hi>I. S.</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp;c. the Rent is behinde and unpaid; in this caſe <hi>I. S.</hi> may not enter by Law, for there is an ancient Maxime, That no man ſhall take advantage of a Condition unleſs he be party or privy to it.</p>
               <p>If the Grantee of a Rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge releaſe parcel of the <note place="margin">Dr &amp; Stud. lib. 2. c 16. 21 H. 7. 2. Co. 1 par. Inſt. fo. 147. b. 148. a. H. 14 Eliz. in C. B. God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt 139. Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing's Caſe. M. 30 Eliz. in B. R.</note> Rent to the Grantour or his Heirs, the Remainder may be apportioned, and the Land ſhall remain chargeable ſtill for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60010:24"/>
reſidue: but if he releaſe in one Acre parcel of the Land char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, then all the Rent is extinct and gone.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor grant a Rent to a Stranger, the Tenant cannot <note place="margin">49 E. 3.15. Finch lib. 1. c. 3. p. 36.</note> Attorn nor put him in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the delivery of an Ox or ſuch like thing; becauſe it is another thing: but upon a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of a Rent, the Sheriff may deliver poſſeſſion by ſuch a thing.</p>
               <p>If one that hath a Leaſe for Years grant his term to a Feme <note place="margin">14 Eliz. Pl. 418. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 42.</note> Covert and to another, or if a Feme ſole and another be Joint-tenants for years, and ſhe take a Husband; yet the Eſtate of the Feme and Jointure doth continue, ſo as the Survivor of the Wife or of the other ſhall have the whole Eſtate.</p>
               <p>If a man grant an Eſtate to a Woman <hi>dum ſola ſuit,</hi> or <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">37 H. 6. 27.26 E. 3.69. 14 H 8. 13. Bract. l. 4. f. 207. Fleta, l. 3. c. 12. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 42. a. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 45.</note>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:60010:24"/>
                  <hi>viduitate,</hi> or <hi>quamdiu ſe bene geſſerit,</hi> or to a man and a woman during the Coverture, or as long as the Grantee dwells in ſuch an houſe, or ſo long as he pays 10 pound, &amp;c. or until the Grantee be promoted to a Benefice, or for any like incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time; in all theſe caſes, if it be of Lands or Tenements, the Leſſee hath in judgment of Law an Eſtate for Life determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, if Livery and Seiſin be made.</p>
               <p>And if it be of Rents, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſons, or any other thing that <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 42. a.</note> lies in Grant, he hath a like E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate for Life by the delivery of the Deed.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for another man's Life die, living the other man, <note place="margin">Brit. f. 83. Fleta l. 3. c. 12. Brac. l. 4. f. 170. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 41. b.</note> he that doth firſt enter upon the Eſtate after his death ſhall be Tenant <hi>pur auter vie,</hi> that is, Tenant for the other man's Life, and ſhall be liable to the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60010:25"/>
of the Rent reſerved, and in Law is called an Occupant, becauſe his Title is by his firſt Occupation.</p>
               <p>And ſo if a Tenant for his <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 27 Aſſ. p. 31. Pl. Com. fo. 28. b. in Col hirſt's Caſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rr 303.</note> own Life grant over his Eſtate to another, if the Grantee die, living Tenant for Life; in this caſe he that firſt enters ſhall be an Occupant: in like manner it is of an Eſtate created by Law; for if Tenant by the Courteſie or Tenant in Dower grant over his or her Eſtate, and the Grantee dieth during their Lives, in this caſe alſo there ſhall be an Occupancy.</p>
               <p>But there can be no Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant <note place="margin">Co. ibid.</note> againſt the King, for <hi>nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tempus occurrit Regi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It were good, ſaith my Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> to prevent the incertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">11 H. 4.42. 17 E. 3.48 Dyer, 8 El. 253. Co. 1 par. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. f. 41. b.</note> of an Eſtate of the Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, by adding theſe words, [To have and to hold to him and his Heirs during the life of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60010:25"/>
                  <hi>Ceſtui que vie:]</hi> and this ſhall prevent the Occupant.</p>
               <p>And if a man hath an Eſtate <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. ibid.</note> already for another's Life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the words before named, then it is good for him to aſſign his Eſtate to divers and their Heirs during the Life of <hi>Ceſtui que vie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for 20 years of Lands and Tenements grant <note place="margin">Perkins, 693.</note> the ſame Lands for parcel of the years to a Stranger, reſerving to himſelf 20 ſhill. in this caſe he may diſtrain for the Rent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, or have an Action of Debt at his pleaſure, becauſe by common intendment he is to have the ſame Land after the years determined, becauſe he hath granted but parcel of the years, ſo that the Remainder remains in him.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Ceſtui que uſe</hi> leaſe his Land in Uſe for term of <note place="margin">Perkins, 692.</note> Years, reſerving Rent by word
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60010:26"/>
of mouth; in this caſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſtrain for the Rent reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, becauſe no Reverſion doth remain in him; but it is ſaid he may have an Action of Debt for it, but ſome doubt of it.</p>
               <p>If I leaſe Lands to another <note place="margin">Perkins, 91. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 46. b.</note> for Years, the term to begin at the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> next, and before the Feaſt the Leſſee grants his term to a Stranger; this is a good Grant, for he hath an Intereſt before Entry which may be granted over.</p>
               <p>If Rent be granted to me, I <note place="margin">Perkins, 91.</note> may grant it away to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, before I be ſeiſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>If a man grant to another <note place="margin">Perkins, 108.</note> Common of Paſture for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10 Kine in Lands in ſuch a Town, though the Grant be general, yet the Grantee ſhall not have Common but in Lands Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monable, ſo as the Grant ſhall extend but to Paſture-grounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60010:26"/>
Tenant at Will cannot grant <note place="margin">27 H. 6. f. 3. b. Kitchin, p. 237. a.</note> over his Eſtate, for he hath no Intereſt certain.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to Baron <note place="margin">Hil. 17 El. in B. R. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 46. b.</note> and Feme for term of their Lives, the Remainder to the Executors of the Survivor of them, if the Husband grant away the term and die, yet this ſhall not bar the Wife.</p>
               <p>If the Husband and Wife be ejected of a Term in the right <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 46. b. 37 Aſſ. p. 11. Pl. Co. 418. b.</note> of his Wife, and the Husband bring an <hi>Ejectione firme</hi> in his own name, and do recover, &amp; die; in this caſe his Executors ſhall have it, and not the Wife, ſon the Recovery in his own name did veſt the Term in himſelf.</p>
               <p>If a man be poſſeſt of a Term <note place="margin">Co. ibid. Pl. Co. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. b. Dame Hale's Caſe. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 351. a. See Finch l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 5. p. 72. &amp; Dyer 264. b<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Herne's<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Law of Conv. p. 81, &amp; 82.</note> of 40 years in right of his Wife, and make a Leaſe for 20 years, reſerving Rent, and die; here the Executors of the Husband ſhall have the Rent for that Term, but the Wife ſhall have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60010:27"/>
the Remainder of the Term when the 20 years is out; but if he had granted the whole Term, then ſhe had got no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
               <p>A Releaſe made to Tenant <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. fo. 270. a. 49 E. 3.28.32 H. 6.8 Co. ibid f. 46. b. Perkins, 602. See the Clerk of Aſſize, p. 50.</note> for Years before his Entry to encreaſe his Eſtate is void; but a Releaſe of the Rent before Entry is good. The Tenant may grant away his Intereſt to another before Entry; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Leſſor die before Entry, yet the Leſſee not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding may enter into the Lands; or if the Leſſee die before Entry, his Executors or Adminiſtrators may enter: and if the Leaſe be made to two, and one die before En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, yet his Intereſt ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives.</p>
               <p>The Leſſor cannot grant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. fo. 46. b.</note> the Reverſion (before the Leſſee's Entry) by the name of a Reverſion,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60010:27"/>
If a man grant to a Leſſee for <note place="margin">12 El. 381. Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 15. Vid. Lutterell's caſe. 43 El. in B. R. Co. 4 lib. f. 86. &amp; Co. 1 par Inſt. f. 41. a. Vide Co. 5 l. in Spencer's caſe.</note> years, that he ſhall have ſo many Eſtovers as ſhall ſerve to repair his Houſe, or that he ſhall burn within his Houſe, or ſuch like, during the Term; this is appurtenant to the Land, and ſhall run with the ſame as a thing appurtenant in whoſe hands ſoever the ſame cometh.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for years grant a Rent-charge and ſurrendreth, <note place="margin">1 El. 198. Finch, lib. 1. cap. 3. p. 27. Noye's Maximes, p. 7.</note> the Rent ſhall be paid during the Term to the Stranger.</p>
               <p>If 2 Tenants in common do <note place="margin">Pl. Com. Hill &amp; Grange's Caſe. 171. 2 &amp; 3 P. &amp; M. 140. b. 161. b. Finch, l. 1. c. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 63. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 197. a.</note> grant a Rent of 10 ſhill. this is ſeveral, and they ſhall be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with 20 ſhill. Rent; but if they make a Leaſe and reſerve 10 ſhill. Rent, they ſhall have no more but onely 10 ſhill. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. N. B. 223. Mich. 3 Jac. in C B. Co. 1 par. Inſt f. 52. b. 45 El. in B. R. Dumpor's Caſe. Co. 4 l. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>19 Hern's Law of Conveyances, 110.</note> that the Leſſee or his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſigns ſhall not aliene the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes without ſpecial licence of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60010:28"/>
the Leſſor, &amp;c. and after the Leſſor giveth licence to aliene the ſame or any part; in this caſe the Leſſee may aliene and his Aſſigns <hi>ad infinitum</hi> without any more Licenſe, for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſo is determined for ever; and if the Leſſor die before the Leſſee aliene, yet that does not countermand it.</p>
               <p>If the words of a Leaſe be, <note place="margin">M. 3. E. 6. Dyer 65 66. Hughes's gr. Abr. 1 part, p. 417.</note> that it ſhall not be lawful for the Leſſee to aliene without the aſſent of the Leſſor, on pain of Forfeiture; this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint continueth but du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Life of the Leſſor and Leſſee.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for years deviſe <note place="margin">Dyer f. 75. Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el's Inſt. p. 142, 143. Bro. Chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels 23. Don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 57. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 81.</note> his whole term to <hi>A,</hi> provided if he die while <hi>I. S.</hi> is alive, then the Reſidue ſhall remain to <hi>I. S; A</hi> alienes and dies: in this caſe <hi>I. S.</hi> is without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe for <note place="margin">27 H. 8.19. Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 65.</note>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60010:28"/>
years, reſerving Rent to him, <note place="margin">Mich. 5 Jac. <hi>inter</hi> Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton <hi>&amp;</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win in B. R. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 47. a. Goldsbor. Rep. p. 148. pl. 68. Vid. <hi>Pacis Conſultum,</hi> p. 92.</note> without naming his Heirs, the Rent ſhall then determine upon his death, if he die within the Term; or if it be to him and his Aſſigns or Executors, it is all one: but if it be reſerved ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally without ſhewing to whom, it ſhall go to his Heirs.</p>
               <p>If a man leaſe Land to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <note place="margin">See 17 El. in B. R. <hi>inter</hi> Pepal <hi>&amp;</hi> Hammington. Poph. 117, &amp; 118.</note> by Deed indented, except and alwaies reſerved to the Leſſor all great Trees growing upon the ſame Land; by this Leaſe the great Trees ſhall not paſs.</p>
               <p>If two Copartners make a <note place="margin">Finch l. 1. c. 3. p. 9.</note> Leaſe, reſerving Rent, they ſhall have this Rent in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon as they have<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but if afterwards they grant the Reverſion excepting the Rent, then they ſhall be Joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants of the Rent.</p>
               <p>If a man let Lands for years, <note place="margin">Dyer 56, &amp; 82. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 148. b. Hughes's gr. Abr. p. 193. 1 par c. 6.</note> reſerving Rent, and a Stranger
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60010:29"/>
doth recover part of the Land, then the Rent ſhall be apporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, that is to ſay divided, and the Leſſee ſhall pay, having reſpect to that which is reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and to that which yet remaineth in his hands, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the value.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe of a <note place="margin">1 &amp; 2 P. &amp; M. 104. Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 18. Perkins 643. 11 H. 4. 2. Philipps Pr. of Law, p. 122.</note> Mannor except an Acre, this Acre is no part of the Mannor as to the Leſſor, but as to him that hath right to demand the Mannor, by an eigne Title it remains parcel, and therefore he ſhall make no fore-priſe in his. Writ.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe of a Mannor excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Services, the Exception <note place="margin">Finch. ibid. p. 53.</note> is void, for it is parcel of the thing let.</p>
               <p>If one make a Leaſe excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Cloſe and Wood, now <note place="margin">14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> H. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> the Law giveth him a way to come to it.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor make a Feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 59.</note>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:60010:29"/>
and the Leſſee for years giveth leave to the Leſſor to make Livery and Seiſin of the premiſſes, ſaving to himſelf his Leaſe, and he doth ſo; here the Term is not ſurrendred, for the Leſſee had an Intereſt which could not be ſurrendred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his conſent to ſurrender, and here no ſuch intent doth appear, wherefore he may enter and have his Term, and the Rent is renewed: but it is otherwiſe with a Leſſee for Life, for there the Rent is extinct.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for years do take a new Leaſe for more years, this <note place="margin">Perkins 117. Vide Watt &amp; Maid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well's Caſe, Hil. 3 Car. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. 1302. B. R. Hutton's Rep. 104.</note> is a Surrender in Law of the old Leaſe.</p>
               <p>A Leſſee for years cannot ſurrender before his Term be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, <note place="margin">Perkins 601. Noye's Maximes, 74.</note> neither can he ſurrender part of his Leaſe, but he may grant part of it.</p>
               <p>If two Joynt-tenants in Fee are of one Acre of Land, and <note place="margin">5 E. 3.19. &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Perkins, 80.</note>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:60010:30"/>
leaſe the ſame Acre to a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for Life, and the Leſſee granteth his Eſtate to one of the Leſſors; this is a Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the whole Acre, and not for a Moiety. <hi>Tamen quaere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for Life of an Acre of Land leaſe the ſame Acre to his Leſſor for years, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder to a Stranger in Fee; this is no Forfeiture, though he do make Livery and Seiſin to the Leſſor.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for Life or Years <note place="margin">Herne's Law of Convey. p. 76. Perkins, pl. 609.</note> of Land ſay to his Leſſor, that he will occupy his Lands no longer which he holdeth of him for Life or Years, and ſo wills him to enter; in this caſe if the Leſſor conſent, it is a good Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render.</p>
               <p>But if the Leſſee for Life or <note place="margin">1 Aſſ. p. 20. Tr. 8 E. 3.46. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, 117.</note> Years of a Houſe and Lands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move his goods out of the Houſe and Land, by reaſon of the greatneſs of the Rent, or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60010:30"/>
becauſe he is behinde in his Rent, or for any other cauſe, and the Leſſor do enter into the Houſe and Lands; this is no Surrender of the Tenant.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for Years aſſign <note place="margin">37 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. B. R. Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and Siddal's Caſe, cited in Co. 3. l. in Walker's Caſe there.</note> over his Term and die, his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors ſhall not be charged for Rent due after his Death. <hi>Noye's Maximes, p.</hi> 72.</p>
               <p>If the Executors or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators <note place="margin">Co. ibid. in Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker's Caſe <hi>ut ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</hi> Noye's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximes, p. 72.</note> of a Leſſee for Years do aſſign over their Intereſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth an Action of Debt lie againſt them for Rent due after the Aſſignment.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee aſſign over his <note place="margin">Marrow &amp; Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin's Caſe. P. 41 Eliz. Rot. 2485. Vide March &amp; Brace's Caſe. M. 11 Jac. in B. R. Bulſt. 2 part 151. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 110.</note> Term, the Leſſor may charge which of them he will; but if he once accept of the Rent from the Aſſignee knowing of the Aſſignment, he cannot then after bring an Action of Debt againſt the Leſſee for Rent due after the Aſſignment.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor grant away the <note place="margin">36 Eliz. Ungle &amp; Glover's Caſe.</note>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:60010:31"/>
Reverſion after the Aſſignment <note place="margin">Vid. Co. 3 l. in Walker's Caſe there: and ſee Humble &amp; Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver's Caſe. M. 36. El. in B. R. Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, 55.</note> of the Leſſee; in this caſe the Grantee cannot have an Action againſt the Leſſee for the Rent, becauſe there is no privity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
               <p>If a Tenant for Life enfeoff <note place="margin">19 E. 3. Surr. 8. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 42. a.</note> him in Remainder for Life, this is a Surrender, and no Forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>If a Tenant for Life make a <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 13 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Dower 95.</note> Leaſe by Deed, or without Deed, to him in Remainder or Reverſion, and after he in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder taketh wife and dieth; in this caſe ſhe ſhall not be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed, for the Tenant for Life ſhall injoy the Land again, for it cannot be a Forfeiture, becauſe he in Remainder was a party; and Surrender it cannot be, for that his whole Eſtate was not given.</p>
               <p>If a Tenant for Life take an <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 42. a. 29 Aſſ. p. 64.</note> Husband, and by Deed inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted they make a Leaſe to him
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60010:31"/>
in the Reverſion for the Life of the Husband, reſerving a Rent; this is neither Forfeiture nor abſolute Surrender, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the laſt Caſe mentioned.</p>
               <p>But if a Tenant for Life take Husband, and they by Deed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented make a Leaſe to him in Reverſion for the Life of the Wife, reſerving Rent; this is a Surrender, for their whole Eſtate is granted, and the Reſervation is void.</p>
               <p>If a Leſſee for 20 years take <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. inſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 218. b. Pl. Com. in Fulmerſton's Caſe. 107. b. Vid. Poph. Rep f 9. V. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 73, &amp; 74. Finch, l. 1. c 4. p. 62. 1 &amp; 2 P. &amp; M. 107.</note> a Leaſe for 10 years to begin preſently, upon Condition if ſuch a thing be not done to be void: now the firſt Leaſe is ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred in Law; and though the ſecond Leaſe be void upon the Condition broken, yet the Surrender remaineth good.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe for years be made to a man without any Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <note place="margin">Perkins, 536.</note> the Leſſee ſhall be ſeiſed to his own uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:60010:32"/>
If a man make a Leaſe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 1. c. 24. See<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Clerk of Aſſize. p. 63.</note> and his Heirs for 20 years, intending that his Heirs ſhall have it; yet if the Leſſee die, notwithſtanding the intent, the Executors, and not the Heir, ſhall have it.</p>
               <p>If a man let a Houſe <hi>cum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pl. Com. f. 85. b. &amp; f. 270, 273. 31 H. 8. tit. Leaſe 55.23 H. 8. tit. Feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 53.</note> no Lands paſs; but if it be <hi>cum omnibus terris perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</hi> here the Lands uſed with the ſame do paſs. <hi>Herns L. of Con. p.</hi> 104.</p>
               <p>If a man take a Leaſe of his <note place="margin">Br. Eſtoppel 221. M. 31, 32 El. in C. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ondon's Caſe adjudged. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 47. b. Vide Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Eſtoppel.</hi>
                  </note> own Land by Deed indented, he is then concluded to ſay that the Leſſor had nothing in the Land at the time of the making of the ſaid Leaſe, but after the Leaſe is out the Eſtoppel is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
               <p>If two Joynt-tenants are of a <note place="margin">24 Car. See Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verley's Caſe. Clayton's Rep. p. 111. pl. 189. &amp; ſee Green's Caſe An. 1650. Idem p. 146. pl. 265.</note> Leaſe for Years, and one bid the other go out of the Houſe, and he does ſo; in this caſe he may have an <hi>Ejectione firme</hi> againſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60010:32"/>
his fellow as well as if he had put him out by force.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of Payments, Rents, Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Confirmations, Extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhments, Demands, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entries, Limitations, &amp;c. of Leaſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the Leſſee be to pay his Rent to his Leſſor at <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vide Clun's Caſe 11 Jac. in B. R. Co. 10 lib. f. 227. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 202. a. And ſee Hare &amp; Savil's Caſe. M. 7 Jac. in C. B. Brownloe's 2 part, p. 273. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 23.</note> and <hi>Martinmas,</hi> or within 15 daies next after either of the ſaid Feaſts; in this Caſe the Tenant need not pay till the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day, for that is the legal day, and the other onely a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary day of Payment: and if there be a Clauſe, that if the Rent be behind by the ſpace of 15 daies after any of the ſaid daies of payment, then the Leaſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60010:33"/>
to be void; in this caſe the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee ſhall have 30 daies after ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Feaſts to ſave his Leaſe: but if the Clauſe in the Leaſe be, that if the Rent be behind for the ſpace of 15 daies next after either of the ſaid Feaſt-daies of payment; here the Tenant hath but 15 daies onely allowed him: and ſo the diverſity is to be noted.</p>
               <p>If a Tenant in Tail let part <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 44. b. Vid. Lord Mount-joy's Caſe. Co. 5. l. f. 3. Anno 31, 32 Eliz. in B. R.</note> of the Land accuſtomably let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, reſerving the Rent <hi>pro Rata</hi> or more, this is a good Leaſe for ſuch Lands: or if the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomable Rent were formerly payable at four Feaſts, and now it is reſerved and payable all at one Feaſt, yet it is good enough.</p>
               <p>If a man leaſe for Years, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <note place="margin">11 Jac. in B. R. Clun's Caſe. Co. 10 l. f. 227. See Hare &amp; Savil's Caſe. M. 7 Jac. in C. B. Brownl. Rep. 2 part. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>73. V. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 22, &amp; 23.</note> Rent at the Feaſts of the <hi>Annunciation</hi> and <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> or within 15 daies after; here if the Leſſor dy after either of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60010:33"/>
the Feaſts and before the 15 daies be out, the Heir ſhall then have the Rent; for the disjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive is added for the benefit of the Tenant; and the firſt day is but voluntary, but the legal payment is at the end of the 15 daies: and if the Leſſee before the day pay the Rent, this is voluntary, and not ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but it is good to give Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, if payment be in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and the Leſſor die at Noon; though this payment be volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary too, yet it is ſatisfactory againſt the Heir.</p>
               <p>If a man leaſe for Years, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <note place="margin">See Manley and Jennings Caſe. Paſch. 10 Jac. in C. B. Brownlo. Rep. 2 par. p. 176. Noye's Maximes p. 80. 6 E 6. Br. Tender 20.</note> Rent at <hi>Martinmas</hi> and other Covenants, if the Leſſee be bound in an Obligation to pay the Rent preciſely; in this caſe he muſt ſeek the Leſſor to pay him: but if he be bound to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Covenants, &amp;c. he may then tender it upon the Land, (if no other place be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60010:34"/>
agreed upon) and it ſufficeth, for the payment is of the nature of the Rent reſerved.</p>
               <p>Rent payable at a day, the <note place="margin">1 Mar. 172. b. Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 38. Noye's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximes, p. 81. Vide Wade's Caſe. 43 Eliz. C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 111. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 30.</note> party hath all the day till Night to pay it: but if it be a great ſumme, as 500 or 1000 pound, he muſt then be ready as long before Sun-ſet as the mony may be told; for the other is not bound to tell it in the Night.</p>
               <p>If a Parſon let his Glebe to a Lay-man, the Leſſee ſhall pay <note place="margin">32 H. 8. Bro. Diſmes 17. Finch, l. 2. c. 1. p. 88.</note> Tithes to the Parſon beſides the Rent, becauſe they are of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Right.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe for <note place="margin">See Clun's caſe. 11 Jac. Co. 10. l. f. 227.</note> Years, rendring Rent at the Feaſt of St. <hi>Michael;</hi> in this caſe if the Leſſor die on <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmas-day</hi> in the morning, if the Rent be unpay'd, the Heir ſhall have it; but if the Tenant pay it that morning before the Leſſor die, the Executors ſhall then have it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:60010:34"/>
If a man leaſe a Stock of Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 47. b. &amp; 292. b. F. N. B. 267.</note> or other goods, rendring Rent at ſeveral daies, he ſhall not have at Action of Debt till all the daies be expired; and ſo it is upon an Obligation; for theſe are perſonal Contracts: but in caſe of a Leaſe for Years, which is a real Contract, it is otherwiſe; for there the Leſſor may have an Action of Debt after every day, or he may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain.</p>
               <p>A man is not bound to pay an Annuity without an Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <note place="margin">See in Pennant's Caſe, 38 Eliz. Co. 3. l. Perkins, 780.</note> but a Rent-ſervice or Rent-charge he is.</p>
               <p>If the King make a Leaſe, <note place="margin">Vide in Co. 4 lib. Borou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hs's Caſe, 38 Eliz. in B. R. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 201. b. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee Goldsbor. Rep. p. 124<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pl. 9. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 27.</note> rendring Rent, without limiting any place or to whoſe hands, the Leſſee may either pay it to the Exchequer, or to the Bailiffs or Receivers of the King: when a Common perſon appoints no place of payment, the Law ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points it to be upon the Land,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60010:35"/>
and there the Demand muſt be made, as is ſhewed afterwards in this Chapter.</p>
               <p>If two Joynt-tenants be, and they make a Leaſe for Years by <note place="margin">5 E 4.4. Co. 1 part Inſt. f 47. a. Co. 8 l. f. 70, 71.</note> paroll or Deed-poll, reſerving a Rent to one of them; yet this ſhall enure to them both: but if it be by Deed indented, it ſhall enure to him alone by way of Concluſion.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be of Land and <note place="margin">Trin. 35 H. 8. Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er 56. 2 Mar. Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er 100. and ſee 20 El. Dyer 361.</note> Sheep, and the Sheep die, or part of the Land is ſurrounded with the Sea; ſome are of opinion that the whole Rent ſhall iſſue out of the reſt. <hi>Tamen quaere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man leaſe Land and die <note place="margin">See Goldsbor. Rep. p. 98. pl. 17. Trin. 30 El. Vide Herne's Law of Conv. p. 22, &amp; 24.</note> before one of the Rent-daies, the Heir ſhall have the Rent due at the next day after his death; but if there were any Rent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear at the Rent-day before the Leſſor's death, the Executors or Adminiſtrators ſhall have that, and may either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60010:35"/>
or have an Action of Debt for it.</p>
               <p>The Leſſor upon a Leaſe at <note place="margin">Co. on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. f. 57. b.</note> Will may diſtrain for Rent ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rear; but if he impound the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs in the ground letten at Will, the Will is then deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
               <p>Upon a Leaſe for Years a man may reſerve the Rent to be <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. 142. a. and ſee Perkins, 696.</note> in the delivery of Hens, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, Geeſe, Turkies, Oxen, Sheep, Roſes, Spurs, Bows, Shafts, Horſes, Hawks, Pepper, Cumine, Wheat, or other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit that lieth in Render, Office, Attendance, and ſuch like, as well as in paying of Mony.</p>
               <p>If the Heir make a Leaſe for <note place="margin">7 H. 5.4. Co. on L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t. f. 42. a.</note> Life reſerving a Rent, againſt whom the Mother recovers her Dower and dieth, the Leſſee ſhall have the Land again for his Life, and the Rent is revived.</p>
               <p>The Acceptance of the Rent <note place="margin">22 H. 8. Br. Acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance 14.</note> upon a void Leaſe will not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60010:36"/>
make the Leaſe good again; but <note place="margin">Vide Browning's Caſe. Pl. Co. 136.</note> if it be onely voidable, it wil.</p>
               <p>The Acceptance of a Rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to begin preſently, is a Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 70.</note> of the Rent before any Entry; but otherwiſe if it be to begin <hi>in futuro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Acceptance of a Rent which <note place="margin">See Co. 3. l. in Pennant's Caſe there.</note> is not <hi>in Eſſe</hi> nor due to him that accepts it doth not affirm the Leaſe: as where Lands are given to the Husband and Wife, and the Heirs of the body of the Husband, and he leaſes the ſame and dies, and the Iſſue accepts the Rent of the Leſſee in his Mother's life, and after ſhe dies; now the Iſſue may avoid the Leaſe, for when he accepted the Rent, it was due to his Mother, and not to him.</p>
               <p>If the Succeſſor of a Parſon <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4 H. 8. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> H. 8. Br Dean <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. Leaſes 52 See Co. 3. l. fo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5, 66. in Pennant's Caſe See Revel &amp; Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>'s Caſe. Goldsb. Rep. pa. 138. pl. 44.</note> or Vicar accept the Rent of a Leaſe for Years made by his Predeceſſor, yet it is worth nothing; for the Leaſe is void
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60010:36"/>
by Death: but it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of a Leaſe for Life.</p>
               <p>But if the Succeſſor of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 2 F. 6 Br. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaſes 33. 32 H. 8. Dyer 46.</note> Abbot or Prior, accept the Rent upon a Leaſe for Years, he ſhall never avoid it, for it was but voidable onely, and his acceptance hath now confirmed it.</p>
               <p>If he that hath Rent-Service <note place="margin">See Hopkins &amp; Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on's Caſe vouched in Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant's C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Co 3. l. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 40. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 373. a. 11 H. 4. 55. 10 Eliz. Dyer 271.</note> or Rent-Charge accepts the Rent due at the laſt day, and gives an Acquittance for it, all the Arrearages due before are thereby diſcharged.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Tail make a Leaſe for 40 years, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence <note place="margin">Pl Co. f. 437. a. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 46. b.</note> 10 years after his Death, rendring Rent, and after he dies, and the Iſſue enters and enfeoffs <hi>B,</hi> the 10 years expires, &amp; then the Leſſee enters; if <hi>B.</hi> accept the Rent, the Leaſe is good.</p>
               <p>If the Husband and Wife let the Land of the Wife for years, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tamen quaere.</hi> P. 5 Mar Dyer 160. and ſee 4 Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Dyer 141. Gough's Caſe.</note> rendring Rent, and after the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:60010:37"/>
Husband dies, and ſhe before any day of payment takes ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who accepts the Rent and dies; by this the Leaſe is affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for Life leaſe Lands for years and dies, the Leaſe is void, and the Rent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved upon the Leaſe is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and Acceptance by him in Remainder will not make it good; for when it is once void by Death, no Acceptance after will make it good.</p>
               <p>If the Husband and Wife let the Lands of the Wife for <note place="margin">3 H 6. f. 22 H. 6. f. ibid. 21 H. 6.24. &amp; Kitchin p 234. B. Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance.</hi>
                  </note> years, rendring Rent, and the Husband dies, if the Wife ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Rent, it is a good Leaſe.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Dower leaſe for years and die, the Leaſe is void, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> H. 8. Br. Tit. Aunceſt. 14.</note> and Acceptance of the Rent by the Heir will not make it good again.</p>
               <p>If a man ſeiſed in Fee let for <note place="margin">1 F. 6. Br. 18 and ſee Finche's Law l. 1. c. 4. p. 68.</note>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:60010:37"/>
10 years, and after ſelleth the Land, and taketh back an Eſtate to him and his Wife, and then the Husband and Wife let for 20 years, reſerving Rent, and the Husband dieth, the Wife accepts the Rent during the firſt 10 years; in this caſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Leaſe is not affirmed, for <note place="margin">21 Eliz. 563. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips Prin. of Law, p. 164.</note> the Acceptance of the Rent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Leaſe beginneth, and ſo before any Rent be due, is no Acceptance at all.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe for Years may be <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 78.</note> confirmed for a time, or upon Condition, or for a piece of the Land; but if it be a Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenement, it ſhall enure to the whole abſolutely.</p>
               <p>There is a diverſity between <note place="margin">See in Pennant's caſe, 38 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liz. Co. 3. l. f.</note> a Leaſe for Life and for Years. In caſe of a Leaſe for Life, though the Concluſion of the Condition be that it ſhall be void, yet acceptance of the Rent due after the breach doth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:60010:38"/>
affirm it and make it good again; for the Free-hold being created by Livery cannot be determined before Entry.</p>
               <p>If a Prebend leaſe for 70 years, and Patron Dean and <note place="margin">See <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ca. 37 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l in C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 81.</note> Chapter confirm the Demiſe aforeſaid in form aforeſaid made for 51 years and no farther; this is a Confirmation of all the Term: but if they had recited the Leaſe, and confirmed the Land for 51 years, this had been good. But by whatſoever words they confirm a Leaſe for Life, or Gift in Tail for part, this ſhall confirm all, becauſe they are intire.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant of the Land and a Stranger join in a Leaſe for <note place="margin">Co. 1 p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> H. 4. 1. 27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 8.16.</note> Years by Deed indented of the ſame Land, this is the Leaſe of the Tenant onely and Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Stranger; and yet the Leaſe as to the Stranger works by Concluſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:60010:38"/>
If two ſeveral Tenants of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <note place="margin">Co. ibid.</note> Lands join in a Leaſe for Years by Deed indented, theſe be ſeveral Leaſes, and ſeveral Confirmations of each of them, and work not by way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
               <p>If <hi>B,</hi> who is Tenant for Life <note place="margin">Co. ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Vid. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port's caſe, M. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7 El. in B. R. Co<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. f. 15. Vide Ellis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Chowne's caſe 44 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. in C. B. Rot. 1459.</note> of <hi>C,</hi> and he in the Remainder or Reverſion in Fee, make a Leaſe by Deed indented; in this caſe this is the Leaſe of <hi>B</hi> during the Life of <hi>C,</hi> and the Confirmation of him in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder; and after the Death of <hi>C</hi> it is then the Leaſe of him in Remainder, and Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>B:</hi> and in this caſe there is no Concluſion.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for Life and he in Remainder in Fee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>make a Leaſe <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt f. 45. a. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> H. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. See Bredon's caſe 39 &amp; 40 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>liz. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1. l. f. 76. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dyer 234.</note> by Deed indented, and the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee be ejected during the Term in the Life of Tenant for Life, he muſt then declare in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Leaſe from Tenant
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60010:39"/>
for Life; and if it be after his Death, he then muſt declare of a Leaſe from him in Remainder.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Ceſtui que uſe</hi> make a <note place="margin">Mich. 35 H. 8. Dyer 58.</note> Leaſe for 20 Years the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> to begin at <hi>Mid-ſummer,</hi> and the Feoffees make a Leaſe the ſecond of <hi>May</hi> for 30 years to the Leſſee, to begin at <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummer</hi> alſo; this is no Surren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the firſt Leaſe, but it ſhall enure as a Confirmation for 20 years, &amp; a new Leaſe for 10 years.</p>
               <p>If a Parſon let a Leaſe for <note place="margin">Vide Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 300. See Dyer 69. See Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Law, chap. 4. Philipps Pr. of Law, p. 78.</note> Years of his Glebe-land, if it be confirmed by Patron and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, it ſhall binde the Succeſſor; otherwiſe not.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Tail leaſe his <note place="margin">32 H. 8. Br. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance 13.</note> Lands for 20 years, rendring Rent, and die, and the Leſſee leaſes to another for 10 years, and the Iſſue accepts the Rent of the ſecond Leſſee; this is no Affirmance of the Leaſe, for there is no privity between the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:60010:39"/>
ſecond Leſſee and the Iſſue: contrary, if he accepts it of him as Bailiff of the Leſſee.</p>
               <p>But if the firſt Leſſee had <note place="margin">Bro. ibid.</note> leaſed over all his Term in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of the Land let, and his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignee pays the Rent to the Iſſue in Tail, who accepts it; this affirms the intire Leaſe; for Rent upon a Leaſe for Years is not apportionable.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe to one <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud l. 2. c. 20 f. 93. b.</note> for Life, and after confirm the Eſtate of the Tenant for Life, the Remainder over to <hi>A B</hi> in Fee, this is a void Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der notwithſtanding the intent, for no Remainder can depend upon an Eſtate, but where the Eſtate begins at the ſame time when the Remainder doth; and in this caſe the Confirmation neither inlarged the Leſſee's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, nor gave him a new one.</p>
               <p>But if a Leaſe be made to <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l 2. c. 20. p. 93. b.</note>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60010:40"/>
one for another man's Life, and after the Leſſor confirms the Eſtate to the Leſſee for the Leſſee's own life, the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der over; this is good, for here the Eſtate is inlarged.</p>
               <p>If a man let Lands for Years <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Cibill and Hill's Caſe, M. 30 Eliz. n C. B. Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard's Rep. 110. Vid Noye's Max. p. 70. &amp; Howe &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>om, Hil. 43 El. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ep. p. 125 pl. 15. &amp; p 114. pl. 6. Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e's Law of Conv. p. 118. See in Walker's Caſe, Co. 3. lib. &amp; ſee Goddard's Caſe, Mich. 34 El. Com. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>co. Owe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s Rep. f. 10.</note> or Life, reſerving Rent, and do enter into any part thereof and take the profit, the whole Rent is thereby extinguiſhed, and ſhall be ſuſpended during his holding thereof.</p>
               <p>If there be two Joint-tenants <note place="margin">
                     <hi>M.</hi> 2, 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Dyer 187. &amp; Finch l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p. 13.</note> for Life, and one let his part for years, rendring Rent, and dies; the Term ſhall continue againſt the Survivor, but the Rent is gone.</p>
               <p>If a man have a Leaſe for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r</hi> Whorwood &amp; Hales. Br. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nguiſhment 54. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaſes 63. Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render 52.</note> Years, as Executor to <hi>A,</hi> and after purchaſes the Reverſion of the Land in Fee; the Leaſe is extinct, and yet it ſhall be Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſets
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60010:40"/>
in the hand of the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</p>
               <p>It behoveth ſuch perſons as <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. b. 40 Aſſ. 11. Noye's Maximes, p. 83. Marche's Rep. p. 147. pl. 218. But note, it may be covenanted that the Leſſor ſhall re-enter without Demand, if both parties pleaſe.</note> will re-enter upon their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, to make demand of the Rent at the Houſe upon the Land, if there be one, (if the payment be not appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted elſewhere by the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the parties) where the Leſſor himſelf or his ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Attorney, a little before Sun-ſet, in the preſence of 2 or 3 ſufficient Witneſſes, ſhall ſay, <hi>Here I demand of</hi> R. A. 10 <hi>pound due to me at the Feaſt of St.</hi> Martin <hi>the Biſhop laſt paſt, for a Meſſuage, Barn,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>which he holds of me in Leaſe by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denture for</hi> 20 <hi>years, bearing Date,</hi> &amp;c. and ſo remain there upon the Land the laſt day that the Rent is due to be paid, until it be dark, that he cannot ſee to tell the money.</p>
               <p>But note, this Demand muſt <note place="margin">49 Aſſ. 5. 15 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. Dyer f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>29. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins 838.</note>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:60010:41"/>
be made at the Fore-door of the Houſe, and not at the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door; <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 201. b. 153. a. b. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 28.</note> for if it be, it is not good, becauſe the Demand muſt be at the moſt notorious place, and it is not material whether any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be there or no: and if the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee be in the houſe, and the door open, yet the Leſſor need go no farther then the Fore-door.</p>
               <p>If there be no Houſe, the <note place="margin">Dyer 329. 15 El. Perkins 838. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 202. a. &amp; 49 Aſſ. 5. See a pretty Caſe in Poph. Rep. 58. upon a Leaſe of two Barns, &amp; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſor demanded at the one, &amp; the Leſſee did tender at the other, and it was held to be a good Tender to ſave a Re-entry.</note> Demand muſt be made at the moſt notorious place of the Land, as at ſome High-way leading through the ſame; for if it be either at the back-door of the Houſe, or ſome obſcure place in the ground, it is void, and the Leſſor ſhall not take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage by ſuch Demand for Re-entry, or breach of any other Condition.</p>
               <p>If the Rent be reſerved to be paied at any place from the <note place="margin">See Kidwell's Caſe, Pl. Com. f. 70. &amp; Boroughs's caſe, 38 El. in B. R. Coo. 4. l. f. 73. Co. 1 part inſtit. f. 202. a.</note> Land, yet it is in Law a Rent, and the Leſſor muſt demand it
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:60010:41"/>
at the place appointed by the parties, obſerving the Rules aforeſaid of the moſt notorious place.</p>
               <p>But if the Leſſee come to the <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. cod. Perkins 837. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 29.</note> Leſſor at any place upon the ground at the day of payment, and tender his Rent to the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, this is good enough, and ſhall ſave the Condition, and the Leſſor is bound to receive it, although it were not at the moſt notorious place, nor laſt inſtant of the day; for he may tender it at any time of the day, though the laſt inſtant be the legal time of payment.</p>
               <p>But this Tender muſt be of <note place="margin">Tr. 23 Car. in B. R. Regeſt. Pract. p. 327.</note> the whole Rent, without dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Taxes or Aſſeſsments, or other Charges. <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 202. a. 20 H. 6.30. See Pl. Com. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill. and Grange's caſe, f. 167.172. and Cranly and Kingſwell's Ca. Paſc. 15 Jac rot. 710. Hobart's Rep. f. 207. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 25, &amp; 26, &amp; 29. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> H. 7.3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Where one leaſes Land to another for Years, rendring Rent of the Land at the Feaſts of St. <hi>Ellenmas</hi> and <hi>Martinmas,</hi> or within 15 daies, and for default
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60010:42"/>
of payment to re-enter; in this caſe it is ſatisfactory and lawful for the Tenant to tender it the laſt hour of the laſt day, if the mony may be told in that time; and ſo it ſufficeth for the Leſſor to demand it the ſame hour.</p>
               <p>If a man grant a Rent-charge <note place="margin">Vide Trin. 36 Fl. Thyn &amp; Cholm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley's caſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Goldsb. Rep. p. 186. See Sir Jo. Spen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer &amp; Sir John Poynes caſe, Tr. 5 Jac. in B. R. God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bok's Rep. 154 &amp; Remmington &amp; Kingerbies caſe, 18 Car in B. R. in Styles Rep. 4. Sir Rich. Grobham and Thornbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough's caſe. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart f. 82.</note> to another with Condition, that if the Rent be behind for ten daies after any Rent-day, that the Leſſee, the Executors, &amp;c. ſhall pay 3<hi rend="sup">s</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">d</hi> for every day un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the aforeſaid Rent ſo behind ſhall be ſatisfied; in this caſe the Rent muſt be demanded, or otherwiſe the <hi>Nomine Poenae</hi> ſhall never be recovered. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart fo.</hi> 133. <hi>Howel's Caſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made upon <note place="margin">Pennant's caſe, 38 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. Co. 3. l. 65. Vid. Green's caſe, 18 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. in B R. Leon. Rep. 262. &amp; March &amp; Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie's caſe 40 El. C. B. ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1302. vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in Pennant's caſe. Co. 1 par. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. f. 211. b. Pl. Com. fo. 133. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 26, &amp; 94<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Condition of Non-payment to re-enter, if the Leſſor diſtrain he may not re-enter, but he may accept of the Rent, and yet re-enter; but if he receive the next Rent again, then he
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:60010:42"/>
cannot, for that eſtabliſheth the Leaſe. Entry into an Acre in the name of all is good enough, if the Land lie all in one County.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe for Years be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <note place="margin">38 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l in Pennan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s caſe. Co. 3. l. f. 65. &amp; ſee 40 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. in C. B. Rot. 1302, in March &amp; Curtie's caſe vouched there. Hughes's gr Abr. 1 part, p. 14. C. 10.</note> Rent, with Condition that if the Leſſee aſſign his term, the Leſſor may re-enter; the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee aſſigneth, and the Leſſor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth the Rent of the hands of the Aſſignee, not knowing of the Aſſignment; now not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the acceptance of the Rent, yet the Leſſor may re-enter if he pleaſe, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Rent ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s him not, becauſe he knew not of the Aſſignment.</p>
               <p>In a Leaſe for Years, if the <note place="margin">28 H 8 Dyer 7. Hughes's gr. Ab. 1 par. pa. 240. C. 1.</note> Leſſee covenant that if he, his Executors or Aſſigns, do ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ene, that then the Leſſor ſhall re-enter, and afterwards he makes his Wife Executrix and dies, who takes Husband again,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60010:43"/>
and he alienes; in this caſe the Leſſor may re-enter, for the Husband is Aſſignee in Law.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe which is onely void<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, <note place="margin">21 Car. B. R. Styles Regeſtum Practicale, p. 196. Vide Hanſon &amp; Norcliff's caſe, Hil. 18 J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c. &amp; Amphurſt &amp; Palmer's caſe, P. 19 Jac. Hobart 331.</note> and not abſolutely void, muſt be made void by the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor's entry; but if it be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely void, there needs no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe for Years yielding to him and his <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 1. c 20 p. 35. a. See the Clerk of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſize<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 56.</note> Heirs a Rent, upon Condition that if it be behind by the ſpace of 40 daies, &amp;c. that then it ſhall be lawful to the Leſſor and his Heirs to re-enter, the Rent is behind 40 daies, &amp;c. and is demanded by the Leſſor, (as it ought by Law) and is not paid, and now the Leſſor dieth; in this caſe his Heir may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for a Title of Entry de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends.</p>
               <p>But if the Leſſor had died af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 1. c. 20. p. 35. a. Cl. of Aſſize, p. 57.</note> the Feaſt-day and before the 40<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day, and the Heir there
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60010:43"/>
makes a Demand at the 40<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day; in this caſe he may not enter for non-payment: <hi>ideo nota.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to <hi>A</hi> and <note place="margin">Tooker's caſe, 43 El. Co. 2. l. f. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>B</hi> for their Lives, and after the Leſſor grants the Reverſion to <hi>C</hi> for his Life, to which Grant <hi>A</hi> attorns, and after by his Deed ſurrenders to <hi>C</hi> all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Eſtate and dies; in this caſe <hi>C</hi> may enter and hold in common with <hi>B.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to <hi>A</hi> for Life, and after the Death of <hi>B</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vide M. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 3. 87. Tr. 1 H. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 31. &amp; Perkins 52. And ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. in Boraſton's caſe. Co. 3 lib. f. 19. 32 H. 6. Tit. <hi>Feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; Faits,</hi> 99. &amp; Co. on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. f. 378. a. See the Clerk of Aſſize, p. 60. &amp; Herne's Law of Conv. p. 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Kitchin, f. 155. a.</note> the Remainder to another in Fee; in this caſe if <hi>A</hi> die living <hi>B,</hi> the Remainder is void: and ſo if a Leaſe be made to <hi>R</hi> for Life, the Remainder to the right Heirs of <hi>IS;</hi> this is good if <hi>R</hi> outlive <hi>IS,</hi> otherwiſe it is void.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to <hi>A</hi> for <note place="margin">9 El. Dyer 254. &amp; ſee Pl. Com. 190. Trin. 8 Eliz. Cecil's caſe. Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er 253.</note> 41 years, if he live ſo long, and if he die within the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60010:44"/>
Term, that then the Wife of the aforeſaid <hi>A</hi> ſhall have it for the reſidue of the ſaid years; this Limitation is void, for if <hi>A</hi> die the Term ends, and the Wife ſhall have nothing.</p>
               <p>If a man have an Houſe for 40 years, and deviſe the Houſe <note place="margin">Paſch. 14 El. Dyer 307.</note> to <hi>IS</hi> without limiting any Eſtate; the Deviſee ſhall then have the intire Term, for he may not have for Life, nor at Will, nor for leſſer Term of years.</p>
               <p>But if a man have a Term of 30 years, and grants ſo many of <note place="margin">Br. Leaſes 66. &amp; ſee the Rector of Cheddington's caſe, 40 El. Co. 1. l. f. 153.</note> them as ſhall be behind at his death; this is void for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty, for he may live till all be out, and then nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains.</p>
               <p>If a man let all his Meadow <note place="margin">See Dyer f. 80. in the queſtions there for the L. Willoughby.</note> in <hi>D,</hi> containing 10 Acres; in this caſe, if there be 20 Acres, all paſs.</p>
               <p>There needs no Livery and <note place="margin">Litt. l. 1. c. 7. Vide Herne's Law of Conv. p. 35.</note>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:60010:44"/>
Seiſin upon a Leaſe for Years, but the Leſſee may enter when he will; and if there be Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Seiſin upon ſuch a Leaſe, to have according to the effect thereof, this Livery is void, and the Leſſee ſhall but have an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate for Years.</p>
               <p>A man makes a Leaſe for Years, and after makes a Deed <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 48. b. See Bettiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h's caſe, 33 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. in C. B Co. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> l. f. 31. &amp; ſee Herne's Law of Conv. <hi>ubi ſuprá,</hi> &amp; p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> of Feoffment, and delivers Sei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, the Leſſee being upon part of the premiſſes, and not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor aſſenting to it, this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very is void; for though the Leſſor hath the Free-hold and Inheritance in him, yet the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion is in the Leſſee, and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very muſt be given of the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion: but if the Leſſee be abſent, and hath neither Wife nor Servants (though he have Cattel) upon the ground, then the Livery ſhall be good.</p>
               <p>If a man let Lands or Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <note place="margin">Lit. l. 1. c. 7. Vide Philipps <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. of Law, p. 94.</note> by Deed or without deed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60010:45"/>
for Term of Years, the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der over to another for Life, in Tail or in Fee; in this caſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Seiſin muſt be given by the Leſſor to the Leſſee for Years, otherwiſe nothing paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to them in Remainder: the Reaſons you have before in this Chapter.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſee enter before Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and enjoy, then the Free-hold <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 49. b.</note> and the Reverſion are ſtill in the Leſſor, and he cannot then make Livery to the Leſſee after Entry; for he is then in poſſeſſion, and Livery can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be made to one in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>The Statute of the 21 of <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. gives liberty and <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 46. a. &amp; Raſtall's Recoveries 2. f. 371. a. Wingate's Abr. Stat. p. 405.</note> power to falſify all Recoveries that ſhall be had againſt the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Free-hold through the Knavery of the Leſſors, intending thereby that the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees ſhall be outed before their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60010:45"/>
Term be out; whenas perhaps they pay'd a great Fine at their Income, and ſo it were an hard caſe if they ſhould loſe their Terms upon ſuch Recoveries by Colluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the Dates, Commencements, Continuance, and Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Leaſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEaſes for Life or Years are <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 45. b.</note> of Three natures. Some be good in Law; ſome voidable by Entry; and ſome void with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Entry; ſome <hi>in futuro,</hi> and ſome <hi>in praeſenti:</hi> of all which you have ſeveral Examples in this little Treatiſe.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made for 3 <note place="margin">See Clayton's caſe, 37 Eliz. in C. B. Cook 5 lib. f. 1. 12 Eliz. Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er 286. 14 Eliz. Dyer 307. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 46. b. Noye's Maximes, p. 66. But ſee Osborn and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's caſe, H. 13 Jac. in B. R. Cro. 2 part, 135. See Barwick's caſe, 39 El. in the Exchequer. Co. 5. l. fo. 93. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 14, &amp; 15.</note> years beginning from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, and is delivered the 19
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60010:46"/>
day of <hi>June</hi> 1663; in this caſe the day muſt be taken <hi>incluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vè,</hi> and the Leaſe muſt end the 18 day of <hi>June</hi> in the third year after. But if a Leaſe be made to hold from the day of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or from the day of the Date, or from the Date; here the Leaſe ſhall begin the day after it is delivered, and the day of the delivery is excluſive; and ſo note the diverſity.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Habendum</hi> of a Leaſe <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. ibid. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 15, &amp; 131.</note> be for the term of 21 years, without mentioning when it ſhall begin, it ſhall then begin from the Delivery.</p>
               <p>If an Indenture of Leaſe <note place="margin">Co. ibid. See Goddard's Caſe, 26 Eliz. Co. 2 l. f. 5. See M. 8 Jac. B. R. Oſley &amp; Sr Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſt Hicks's Caſe. Cro. 2 part 263, 264. there being pretty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Date and Delivery of a Deed. Herne's Law of Convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, <hi>ubi ſuprá,</hi> &amp; pa. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> bear date the 30 <hi>Febr.</hi> or 40 of <hi>March,</hi> which is impoſſible; in this caſe if the term be limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to begin from the Date, it ſhall then begin from the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, as if there had been no Date at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60010:46"/>
If Lands deſcend to an Heir, <note place="margin">Noye's Max. p. 67.</note> he may make a Leaſe thereof before his Entry into the ſame.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe to one <note place="margin">ibid. p. 68. 26 H. 8. Bro. Leaſe 48.</note> for 10 years, and the next day after make another for 20 years to another man; this ſecond Leaſe ſhall be good for 10 years after the firſt is expired.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made for 21 <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 45. b. &amp; ſee 40 El. in the Rector of Cheddington's caſe. Co. 1 lib. f. 154. and Herne's Law of Convey. p. 135.</note> years, and after another Leaſe to commence from the end and expiration of the ſaid term of years, and after the firſt Leaſe is ſurrendred; in this caſe the ſecond Leaſe ſhall commence preſently upon the Surrender: but if it had been to commence from the end of the ſaid 21 years; there, though there had been a Surrender, yet it ſhould not have commenced till the term had been out: and ſo note a diverſity between <hi>Terminum Annorum</hi> and <hi>Tempus Annoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60010:47"/>
A man cannot make a Leaſe <note place="margin">See the 39 El. in Barwick's caſe. Co. 5. l. f 93.</note> for Life to commence at a day to come, for he cannot make a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Livery to a future Eſtate; and therefore in this caſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth paſs.</p>
               <p>If <hi>A</hi> ſeiſed of Lands in Fee do grant to <hi>B,</hi> that when he <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 45. b. See many prety caſes in the B. of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>he &amp; Wells's caſe, Co. 6. l. f. 34, 35.</note> payes him 20 s. that then from that time he ſhall have and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy the Land for 21 years, and after <hi>B</hi> paies the 20 s; this is a good Leaſe for 21 years from that time, notwithſtanding the Rule of <hi>Bracton,</hi> That every Leaſe muſt have a certain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ending; <hi>Quia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d certum eſt, quod certum reddi poteſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo if a man leaſes Land <note place="margin">3. M. 1. Br. Leaſes 67. the end.</note> to another till the Leſſee hath levied 20 pound; this is a good Leaſe, notwithſtanding the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <note place="margin">Co 1 part Inſt. f. 45 b. See Say &amp; Fuller's caſe.</note> for ſo many years as <hi>R. A.</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:60010:47"/>
ſhall name, this at the beginning <note place="margin">Pl. Co. Kitchin, p. 235. b. Vide Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipps's Pr. of Law, p. 36.</note> is incertain; but when <hi>R. A.</hi> hath named the years, it is then good for ſo many years as he names.</p>
               <p>If <hi>A</hi> leaſeth his Lands to <hi>B</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 45. b.</note> for ſo many years as <hi>B</hi> hath in the Mannor of <hi>Sale,</hi> and <hi>B</hi> hath 10 years in it; this is a good Leaſe to <hi>B</hi> of the Lands of <hi>A</hi> for the ſaid ſaid 10 years.</p>
               <p>But if a Parſon make a Leaſe <note place="margin">Co. ibid. So reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Hil. 26 El. Rot. 935. in C. B.</note> of his Glebe for ſo many years as he ſhall be Parſon there, this is void for the incertainty; for <hi>Terminus vitae eſt incertus, &amp; licet nihil certius eſt morte,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Brac. l. 2. c. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>nil tamen incertius eſt horâ mortis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Parſon make a Leaſe of his <note place="margin">Co. ibid.</note> Glebe for 3 years, and ſo from 3 years to 3 years ſo long as he continues Parſon; this is a good Leaſe for 6 years, and void for the Remainder: but this muſt be underſtood, if he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60010:48"/>
Parſon ſo long.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to one <note place="margin">See in the 40 El. in the Rector of Cheddington's ca. Co. 1. l.</note> for ſo many years as his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſhall name; this is void for the incertainty.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe for a year, and ſo from year to year during the <note place="margin">Noye's Max. p. 66.</note> Life of <hi>R. A,</hi> is a Leaſe but for 2 years; and if the Termor ſtay longer, he is afterwards but Tenant at Sufferance.</p>
               <p>If I make a Leaſe to <hi>R. B.</hi> to <note place="margin">33 Aſſ. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2 M. 1. Br. Leaſes 67. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 42. a.</note> hold the Lands till 100 pound be paid, and make no Livery of Seiſin; he hath an Eſtate but onely at Will, and may be put out at pleaſure: but if Livery be given, he hath an Eſtate for Life, upon Condition implied, to ceaſe upon the payment of the 100 pound.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe from year to year ſo <note place="margin">14 H. 8.16. Noy's Max. p. 66. Br. Leaſe 13.22.</note> long as both parties pleaſe, is a good Leaſe after Entry in any year for that year, till war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be given to depart.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:60010:48"/>
If a Leaſe be made to <hi>A</hi> and his Aſſigns for his Life and the <note place="margin">See Roſſe's caſe, 41, 42 Fl. Co. 5. l. f. 13. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 12.</note> Life of <hi>B</hi> and <hi>C;</hi> this is a good Leaſe for 3 Lives.</p>
               <p>But if a Leaſe be made for an <note place="margin">See in Co. ſaid 5. Book, in Brude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 34 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. in B. R. &amp; ſee Brownl. 2 part, p. 292.</note> hundred years, if <hi>A</hi> and <hi>B</hi> live ſo long; in this caſe, if either of them die, the Leaſe is ended.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe rendring Rent to <note place="margin">See Co. 5. l. f 111. in Mallery's ca. 43 Eliz. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 142.</note> one and his Heirs, or his Heirs alone, but of a Feoffment <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendum</hi> to one or his Heirs, is but an Eſtate onely for the Life of the Feoffee.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe to <note place="margin">See 3 Jac. Savin's ca. in C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 123.</note> commence after the end or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of a former Leaſe <hi>in eſſe,</hi> and after the firſt Leaſe is out, and the ſecond Leſſee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth not, but he in the Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion enters, and makes a Feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and levieth a Fine with Proclamations, and 5 years paſs without Entry or Claim of the ſecond Leſſee; in this caſe the Fine barrs him: for the Stat.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60010:49"/>
4 <hi>H.</hi> 7. c. 24. ſpeaks of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and a Leaſe for years is an Intereſt within the Statute.</p>
               <p>If an Infant, who is ſeiſed of <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 45. b.</note> Land held in Soccage, make a Leaſe at his age of 15; this is good, and ſhall bind him.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Tail make a <note place="margin">10 E. 3.26. 34 Aſſ. 15.23 E. 3. Dower 130. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 46. a.</note> Leaſe for Years according to the Statute, rendring Rent, and die without Iſſue; now as to him in the Reverſion the Leaſe is void; but if he endow the Wife of that Land, it ſhall be good againſt her: or if Tenant in Tail die without Iſſue, his wife <hi>enſeint</hi> with a Son, and he in Reverſion enters, and after the Wife is delivered; in this caſe the Leaſe is again revived, although it were once void by the Entry of him in Reverſion. <hi>Nota.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Tenant in Fee take a <note place="margin">Co 1 part Inſt. f. 46. a.</note> Wife, and make a Leaſe for Years, and after die, and the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60010:49"/>
Wife is thereof endowed; here ſhe ſhall avoid the Leaſe, but after her Death it ſhall be in force again againſt the Heir.</p>
               <p>If an Husband have a term of years in Right of his Wife, <note place="margin">Idem ibid. b &amp; fo. 35<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Mich. 26, 27 El. adjudged in bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h Court<hi>-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r</hi> Amnor <hi>&amp;</hi> Lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dington. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e 7 Jac. in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning's caſe. Co. 8. l. f. 94.</note> if ſhe die, it remains to him; but if ſhe ſurvive him, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to her, and not to his Executors, without he make diſpoſition of it in his life-time, 14 <hi>El. Pl. Com.</hi> 419.</p>
               <p>If a man leaſe for Life to <hi>I. S,</hi> and the next day leaſes to <hi>W. B.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">37 H. 8 Br. Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes 48. the end.</note> for 20 years; the ſecond Leaſe is void, if it be not a Grant of a Reverſion with Attornment; for in Law the Free-hold is more worthy and perdurable then a Leaſe for Years: yet if the Leſſee for Life die within the Term, the Leaſe for Years is good for the reſt of the years to come.</p>
               <p>If a man licenſe another to <note place="margin">Brownl. 2 part, p. 250. 10 E. 4. f. 4. 5 H. 7. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> enter and occupy his Lands,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60010:50"/>
this is a good Leaſe for Years in Law.</p>
               <p>If a man leaſe for 60 years, and ſo from 60 years to 60 <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. Com. f. 273.29 H. 8. Br. Leaſes 49.</note> years, until 200 years be ended; this is all the ſame Leaſe, and good for the term.</p>
               <p>If a man have a Leaſe for <note place="margin">32 l. Aſſ. 6.</note> 500 years, it is but a Chattel, notwithſtanding the long time.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe for Years, though it be never ſo long, cannot be <note place="margin">H. l. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Car. in B. R. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yles Regeſt. Practicale, p. 197.</note> Intailed, for the nature of a Chattel cannot be turned into an Inheritance.</p>
               <p>If a man ſeiſed of Land in <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Vid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lipps <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. of Law, p. 88.</note> Fee-ſimple make a Leaſe of the ſame to another, To have and to hold the ſame for term of Life, and do not mention whoſe Life; in this caſe it ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to be for the Leſſee's Life; for the Act of every man ſhall be taken moſt ſtrongly againſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>But if Tenant in Tail let <note place="margin">Co. ibid. &amp; f. 183. b. Finch, l. 1. c. 4. p. 60.</note>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:60010:50"/>
ſuch a Leaſe without expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing whoſe Life, it ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to be for the Life of the Leſſor.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe for a thouſand daies <note place="margin">14 H. 8. f. 1. Finch, l. 1. c. 5. p. 67.</note> is a Leaſe for Years.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe for Years and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe <note place="margin">Finch, cod. loco. Co. Lit. f. 207. a.</note> amounteth to a Feoff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>If Joynt-tenant make a Leaſe <note place="margin">Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 97. Mich. 3 Eliz. Dyer, 187. Lit l. 3. c. 3. Co. 1 part Inſt. f 185. a. &amp; 186. a. b. But ſee Dyer f. 178. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n &amp; Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s caſe. Goldsb. p. 187. pl. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> for years of his part, though the Leſſee never had poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or though it be to begin at a day to come, and the Joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant which made it die before the day; yet the Survivor ſhall be bound by the Leaſe, for the Leſſee hath a preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
               <p>But it is otherwiſe of a Grant <note place="margin">Co 1 part Inſt. f. 184. b. Finch, ibid. 5 El. Plo. 203. Brown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Com. 263. b. in Dame Hales caſe.</note> to have a Leaſe, if the Grantee pay 10 pound before <hi>Midſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> next, and the Joynt-tenant which made the Grant die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day; for here is no Intereſt at all, but a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60010:51"/>
till the mony be paid.</p>
               <p>If a man let Land for Life, without ſaying more, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion <note place="margin">Finch, l. 2. c. 3. p. 113. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it.</note> of the Fee-ſimple is in the Leſſor.</p>
               <p>If Tenants for Life or Years of Land make a Feoffment in <note place="margin">Idem ibid. Br. Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſ. 96.</note> Fee, and give Livery, they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit their terms.</p>
               <p>If two take a Leaſe for their Lives, and make partition; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">See Farrington's caſe. Dyer 67. &amp; Cowell's Inſt. p. 199.</note> of them dying, his part immediately reverts to the Leſſor.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to a Feme ſole for 40 years, if ſhe ſo long <note place="margin">See Sayer and Hardye's caſe. Goldsb. p. 179. pl. 112.</note> live ſole and continue unmarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; now if ſhe die, the Leaſe is determined: or if I make a Leaſe for 40 years, if the Leſſee dwell upon the thing let du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the term; here if the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee die, the term is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
               <p>But if it be a Leaſe for 40 years, if the Leſſee dwell upon <note place="margin">Idem in Save's &amp; Hardye's c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe.</note>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60010:51"/>
the thing let during his Life; in this caſe if the Leſſee dieth, the Leaſe continueth.</p>
               <p>If there be two Joynt-te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants <note place="margin">Harbin &amp; Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's caſe, 30 El. Goldsb. Rep. 187. pl. 130.</note> for Life, and the one make a Leaſe for 80 years, to begin af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, and after dies; this is a good Leaſe againſt the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivor.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to the <note place="margin">Brownloe's 2 part p. 206. the end. Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 33. f. 120. a. b. See Cowel's Inſt. p. 193.</note> Husband and Wife, yielding a greater Rent then the Land is worth; in this caſe if the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band die, the Wife may refuſe the occupation of the Land, and ſo be diſcharged of the Rent: but if the Husband overlive the Wife, and die, his Executors, if they have Aſſerts to pay the Rent to the end of the term, may not refuſe thé Leaſe; but if they have not Aſſetts, they may wave the occupation, and by ſpecial pleading diſcharge <note place="margin">Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 31. 4 E. 6.68. b. See Co. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l. in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Brudenel's caſe.</note> themſelves.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to <hi>A</hi> and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60010:52"/>
                  <hi>B</hi> for their Lives, in this caſe if either die, the other ſhall have all during his life, for it is an Intereſt. <hi>Philipps Pr. of Law,</hi> 131.</p>
               <p>If a Woman make a Leaſe at <note place="margin">Henſtead's caſe, 36, 37 El. C. B. Co. 5. l. f. 10. See M. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7 El. in C. B. r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> Will reſerving Rent, and after take Husband, yet the Leaſe at Will continues ſtill: and if a <note place="margin">3 H. 8. Vid. Keil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye's Rep. f. 162. &amp; Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mand.</hi>
                  </note> Feme ſole, who is Leſſee at Will, take Husband, yet the Leaſe at Will is ſtill good.</p>
               <p>If Husband and Wife make a Leaſe at Will of the <note place="margin">Co. 1 part of Inſt. f. 55. b.</note> Wives Lands, reſerving Rent, and the Husband dieth, yet the Leaſe at Will continueth: and ſo it is if two make a Leaſe at Will to two others, if either one of the Leſſors or Leſſees die, yet the Leaſe is good.</p>
               <p>If Tenant at Will leaſe for Years in his own name, it is a <note place="margin">2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> H. 6.3.22 E. 4. 5. Co. 1 par. Inſt. l. 57 a. 12 E. 4.12.</note> Diſſeiſin, and the Leſſor may have Treſpaſs againſt the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee of the Leſſee at Will.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:60010:52"/>
If a man leaſe to one at Will, <note place="margin">21 H. 6. f. 42. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, 237. a.</note> and the Leſſor dies, the Will is gone.</p>
               <p>If I let Lands in which are <note place="margin">9 E. 4. f. 37. per Needham.</note> Mines or Trees, I cannot enter to take the Trees or Mines, but am a Treſpaſſer, unleſs I reſerve ſuch a privilege to my ſelf when I let the Lands.</p>
               <p>All Feoffments, Gifts, Grants <note place="margin">Perkins 16. Co. on Lit f. 253. b. 14 Aſſ. pl. 20. Plo. 18. a. Vide Philipps, Principles of Law, p. 4.</note> and Leaſes made by Dureſs of Impriſonment are voidable, and that not onely by the parties themſelves, but by their Heirs, and by thoſe who have their Eſtates.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor come upon the <note place="margin">Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 57. Vid. Hunt &amp; Downam's caſe, Paſc. 16 Jac. B. R. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. 2 part, 478.</note> ground leaſed, he is no Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſer, for it ſhall be intended that he came to ſee if Waſt were done.</p>
               <p>Although a Leſſee for Years <note place="margin">Styles Regeſtum Practicale. p. 198. Paſch. 1650. in B. R.</note> do loſe his Indenture of Demiſe of the Lands let unto him, yet he ſhall not loſe his term in the Lands let by Indenture which
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:60010:53"/>
is loſt, if it can be proved any way that there was ſuch a term let to him by Indenture, and that it is not determined: and ſo it is of any other Eſtate in Land, if the Deed that created the Eſtate be loſt, if it can be ſufficiently proved that there was ſuch a Deed made, and that ſuch an Eſtate was conveyed by Deed.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for term of years or any other Tenant be outed, or if they die, their Executors, or they if living, ſhall have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable time and free liberty to come and fetch away their U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſils and other goods out of the Leſſor's Houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:60010:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Corn ſown where the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is outed, or the Term determines before it be ripe, who ſhall have it: and alſo of Eſtovers, and Trees blown down, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF Tenant at Will ſow the <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leta, l. 3. c. 13. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 55. a. 11 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 4. f. 90. Vide Philipps Pr. of Law, p. 86.</note> Land, he ſhall have free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to come and cut and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry away his Corn, although the Leſſor put him out before it be ripe.</p>
               <p>But if Tenant for Years ſow <note place="margin">Co. on Lit. f. 55. a. b. Lit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. <hi>Tenant at Will.</hi> See the Clerk of Aſſize, p. 60.</note> the Land, and his term end be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Corn be ripe, the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor ſhall have it, without it be covenanted between them, that he ſhall have his way-going Crop, as they call it in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire:</hi> and the reaſon of this is, becauſe the Tenant did know
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60010:54"/>
when his term would end, and it was his folly to ſow Corn that would not be ripe till the term were expired.</p>
               <p>If Leſſee at Will ſet Roots, or ſow Hemp or Flax or any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 18 E 4.18.10 Aſſ. pl. 6.</note> profit, if after they be planted the Leſſor out him, or if the Leſſor die, yet the Leſſee or his Executors ſhall have that year's Crop.</p>
               <p>But if he plant young Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trees, <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Temps E. 1. Br. 25.</note> or young Oaks, Aſhes, Elmes, &amp;c. or ſow the ground with Acorns, if he be outed by the Leſſor, he ſhall have none of theſe, becauſe they yield not preſent annual profit.</p>
               <p>Every Tenant that hath an Eſtate incertain ſhall have the <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 7 Aſſ. 19.</note> Corn ſown by him, though he be ouſted before it be ripe. <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 10 E. 3.29. See in Sir Henry Knivett &amp; Pool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> caſe, Golds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough's Rep. p. 143. pl. 60. &amp; Co. 5. l. f. 85. See the Clerk of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſize, p. 60.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If Tenant for Life ſoweth the ground, and dy before the Corn be ripe, his Executors
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60010:54"/>
ſhall have it, and Graſs, if it be cut; but not Meadow unmown, for that is part of the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance till it be ſevered.</p>
               <p>The like Law is of the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee <note place="margin">Co. on Lit. f. 55. b.</note> for Years of Tenant for Life.</p>
               <p>If a man be ſeiſed of Land in <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 7 Aſſ. pl. 10. Perkins, 518. Swinburn's Wills, 3 part, ſect. 6. p. 163. Dyer, 316. 8 Aſſ. 21. Vide <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Conſultum,</hi> p. 83.</note> right of his Wife, and ſow the Land and die, his Executors ſhall have the Corn; but if they be Joynt-tenants of Lands, and the Husband ſoweth the ground and dieth, the Wife ſhal then have it.</p>
               <p>If <hi>A</hi> leaſe Land for the life of <hi>B,</hi> and ſow the Land, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Corn be ripe <hi>B</hi> dies, yet notwithſtanding <hi>A</hi> ſhall have the Corn, for his Eſtate was determined by the Act of God.</p>
               <p>The ſame Law is of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <note place="margin">Cowell's Inſt. p. 141. Fulb. par. f. 37. b. Perkins, 513. Swinburn <hi>ubi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Tenant for Life or in Dower, who takes Husband, and he ſows the Land, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60010:55"/>
the Corn be ripe the Wife dies.</p>
               <p>But if a Woman who holds Lands <hi>durante viduitate ſuâ</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">V. Oland's Caſe, 44 El. in B. R. Co. 5. l. f. 116. &amp; Co. on Lit. f. 55. b. Vid. Goldsb. Re. p. 189. pl. 136. Hern's Law of Conv. p. 239.</note> ſow the ground, and then take Husband, here the Leſſor ſhall have the Corn: and ſo if Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant at Will ſow the Land, and then will occupy the Land no longer, he ſhall loſe the Corn: and the reaſon of this is, becauſe that the determination of their Eſtates grew by their own Act.</p>
               <p>A Leaſe made by the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 70. Vid. Stat. 32 H. 8. ch. 28.</note> alone of the Wives Land is void after his death; but if the Leſſee have ſown the Land, he ſhall have the Corn.</p>
               <p>If there be Land-lord and Tenant, and the Land is reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered <note place="margin">Tr. 37 H. 6.35. Perkins, 515. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel's Inſt. p. 142.</note> by a Title paramount againſt the Land-lord; in this caſe if the Tenant have ſown the Land, he that recovered ſhall have the Corn, if it be
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:60010:55"/>
not ſevered before Judgment.</p>
               <p>Note that to every Tenant <note place="margin">Brac. l. 4. f 222, 231, 232. Fleta, l. 4. c. 19, 25, 26, 27. F. N B. 180. 21 H. 6.46. 10 F. 4.3. Vide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel's caſe, 43 Fl, in B. R. Co. 4. l. f. 86, 87. Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Haybote,</hi> &amp; verb. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>bote,</hi> and <hi>Houſebote.</hi> Phili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Pr. of Law, p. 65.</note> for Life or Years the Law, as incident to his Eſtate, giveth him, without proviſion of the party, three kind of Eſtovers; that is <hi>Houſebote,</hi> which is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, viz. <hi>Eſtoverium aedifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi &amp; ardendi,</hi> that is, for repairing the Houſes and burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; then <hi>Ploughbote,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>Eſtoverium arandi,</hi> that is, for mending his Ploughs, Harrows, Wains, and making Rakes and Forks for getting his Hay; and laſtly <hi>Haybote,</hi> and that is <hi>Eſtoverium claudendi,</hi> and this is for repairing and mending his Stack-bars, Gates, Stiles and Hedges: but theſe Eſtovers muſt be reaſonable. <hi>Bote</hi> in the <hi>Saxon</hi> tongue and <hi>Eſtovers</hi> in the <hi>French</hi> tongue in this caſe are all of one ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, that is, to have Compenſation or ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60010:56"/>
for theſe purpoſes.</p>
               <p>Theſe Eſtovers the Leſſee <note place="margin">Co. on Lit. f. 41. b.</note> may take without the Aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Leſſor, unleſs the Leſſee be reſtrained by ſpecial Covenant, for <hi>Modus &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventio vincunt legem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eſtovers granted to be burnt <note place="margin">Finch, l. 1. c 3. p. 15. 12 El. 381. 5 H. 7.1.7. gr. 58. P. 26 H. 8.4. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, 104. Kitchin, f. 51. a.</note> in ſuch an Houſe, ſhall go to him that hath the Houſe by whatſoever Title; for one is inſeparably incident to the other.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for Life or Years cut down Trees, or pull down <note place="margin">Vide Co. 4. l. 31 El. in B. R. in Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lackenden's caſe there; &amp; Co. 11. l. in Lewis Bowles's caſe, 13 Jac.</note> Houſes, or ſuffer them to fall, the Leſſor ſhall have the Trees and Timber of the ſaid Houſes, for the Leſſee had them onely as things annexed to the Land, and he ſhall not have a greater Intereſt in them by this torti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Severance.</p>
               <p>If Timber-Trees be blown down by the wind, the Leſſor <note place="margin">Vide Co. <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prà,</hi> &amp; 16 El Dyer 332. F. N. B. 59 M. 20 E. 3. Waſt 32.</note> ſhall have them, for they are
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60010:56"/>
parcel of the Inheritance, and not the Tenant for Life or Years, unleſs it be to build withall, where Houſes are in decay: but if they be Dotards without any Timber in them, then the Tenant ſhall have ſuch when they are blown down.</p>
               <p>Leſſee for Years or for Life, <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Noye's Max. p. 68.</note> Tenant in Dower or by the Courteſie, have onely a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Intereſt or property in the Trees, as a thing annexed to the Land ſo long as they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed thereunto; but if they or any other ſever the Trees from the Land, then their Intereſt is determined, and the Leſſor may take the Trees as things that are parcel of his Inheritance, the Intereſt of the Leſſee being determined.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:60010:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of Diſtreſſes. Of what things a Diſtreſs may be taken, and how it muſt be uſed, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE word <hi>Diſtreſs</hi> is a <note place="margin">Co. on Lit. f. 96. a.</note> 
                  <hi>French</hi> word, and in <hi>Latine</hi> it is called <hi>Diſtrictio ſive An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtia,</hi> becauſe the Cattel di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained are put into a Streight, which we call a Pound.</p>
               <p>A Diſtreſs muſt be of a thing <note place="margin">14 H. 8. 25.2 F. 2. Tit. <hi>Diſtreſs.</hi> 6 R. 2. Reſcous 11. Co. ibid. f. 47. a. Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 1. c. 5.</note> whereof a valuable property is in ſome body; and therefore Dogs, Bucks, Does, Conies, and the like that are <hi>ferae natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi> cannot be diſtrained, nor an Horſe when a man or woman is riding on him, nor an Ax in a man's hand cutting of wood, for they are for that time privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged.</p>
               <p>Neither can things which are <note place="margin">22 E. 4.36.7 H. 7. 1. b. 22 E. 4.49. b.</note>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:60010:57"/>
for the maintenance and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit <note place="margin">Co. ibid. &amp; Noye's Max. p. 43. Comp. Attorney, p. 124. Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</hi>
                  </note> of Trades be diſtrained for Rent; as an Horſe in a Smith's Shop, nor an Horſe in an Inne, for the Rent thereof, nor the Materials in a Weaver's Shop for making of Cloth, nor Cloth or Garments in a Tailor's Shop, nor Sacks of Corn or Meal in a Mill, for the Rent of the Mill, nor any thing that the Leſſee hath diſtrained for dammage feaſant, for it is in the Cuſtody of the Law.</p>
               <p>A diſtreſs may not be taken <note place="margin">Co. on Lit. f. 47. a. 51 H. 3. Stat. de Diſtrictione Scac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. Bra. l. 4. f. 217. F. N. B. 90. a. Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, l. 2. c. 21. 14 H. 8. f. 29. Finch, l. 2. c. 6. p. 135.</note> of Oxen of the Plough; nor a Mil-ſtone, though it be raiſed up to be picked, ſo long as it lies upon the other Stone; nor Sheep, if there be a ſufficient Diſtreſs beſides; neither may a man ſever Horſes joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or to a Cart.</p>
               <p>Nothing ſhall be diſtrained <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 18 E. 3.4. a. 11 H. 7.14. a. 21 H. 7. 39. b. Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</hi>
                  </note> of which the Sheriff cannot make a Replevin, or that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60010:58"/>
be reſtored again in as good a plight as it was at the time of the Diſtreſs taken.</p>
               <p>Victuals nor Sheafs or <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 21 E. 4. 50. b. 2 H. 4.15. &amp; Finch, l. 2. c. 6. p. 135.</note> Shocks of Corn cannot be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained: but Chariots or Carts with Corn may either for Rent or for Dammage feaſant.</p>
               <p>No man may be diſtrained <note place="margin">Co. ibid.</note> by the Utenſils or Inſtruments of his Trade, as the Ax of a Carpenter, or the Books of a Scholar.</p>
               <p>Neither can Furnaces, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons <note place="margin">Idem, f. 47. b. 20 H. 7. f. 13. 3 E. 3. 21 H. 7.26 Aſſ. 49. 9. Finch, <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</hi> Compleat Att. p. 124.</note> or the like fixed to the Free-hold, nor Fats fixed for a Dier's pan, although the Leſſee may remove them during the term, nor the Windows or Doors of the Houſe whileſt they are on the Hinges, &amp;c. be diſtrained.</p>
               <p>But if they be removed from <note place="margin">Finch, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> off the Hinges, they may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained.</p>
               <p>The Lord cannot diſtrain <note place="margin">21 H. 7.26. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, 63. a.</note>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:60010:58"/>
Tables dormant in the Houſe of his Tenant, nor any thing which cannot be attached in an Aſſize.</p>
               <p>A man may diſtrain the <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 47. b. 7 H. 7.1 b. 10 H. 7.21.</note> Beaſts of a Stranger that come by Eſcape for Rent, though they have not been Levant and Couchant on the ground, ſaith my Lord <hi>Cook.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord may ſell a Diſtreſs <note place="margin">3 H. 7. f. 4. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 61 b. Vide Gomorſall and Wayt's caſe, M. 8 Jac in B. R. Cro. 2 part, 255.</note> taken for an Amercement in a Court-Leet, as the King may ſell the Diſtreſs, becauſe it is a Court of the King's.</p>
               <p>The Lord cannot diſtrain <note place="margin">10 H. 7. f. 21. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 62. a.</note> another man's Horſe in the houſe of one amerced, nor the Robe of another in a Taylor's Shop, where the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Taylor is amerced.</p>
               <p>If a man diſtrain goods or <note place="margin">Finch, l. 2. c. 6. p. 137. 9 E. 4. f. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Kitchin, f. 207. b.</note> Chattells, he may put them where he will, either in Pound covert or overt: but if they take any harm, he
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60010:59"/>
muſt anſwer for them.</p>
               <p>But if they be living Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 47. b. Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 27. Compl. Attorney, p. 125. Fleta, l. 2. c. 20. F. N. B. 89. Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Diſtreſs.</hi>
                  </note> they ought to be put in a common Pound, or elſe in ſome open place, as in his own Cloſe, or anothers by his conſent, ſo that the Owner may come law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to feed them; and notice muſt be given to the Owner where they are, if they be not in a common Pound; and then if they die, it is in the Owner's Defalt: but if they be in a Pound covert, or out of the County, and die for want of meat, then he that diſtrained ſhall anſwer for them.</p>
               <p>Cattel taken Dammage-fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0 H. 7. f. 39. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 207. a.</note> may be impounded in the ſame ground where they are Dammage-feaſant; but goods or Cattel taken for other things may not.</p>
               <p>No man may drive a Diſtreſs <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 47. b. Marlbridg, c. 4. Weſt. 1. c. 16. 2, 3 P. &amp; M. c. 12. Vide Berdſley &amp; Pilkinton's ca. Goldsb. Rep. p. 100. pl. 5. &amp; p. 145. pl. 62. Partridge &amp; Naylor's ca. See Mich. 24 El. in C. B. Godbolt's Rep. 11. Raſtall Tit Diſtreſſes 11. Wingate's Abr. p. 133.</note>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:60010:59"/>
out of the County where it is taken, nor out of the Hundred, but to a Pound overt within 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> miles; neither may a Diſtreſs be impounded in ſeveral places, nor above 4 pence taken for the Fees of impounding one whole Diſtreſs, on pain of 5 pound.</p>
               <p>If a man diſtrain Beaſts Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-feaſant, and put them in <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 27.</note> the Pound overt within the ſame County not above 3 miles out of the Hundred, and the Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſuffers the Beaſts to die for lack of meat; then he that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained them is at his liberty to take his Action of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs.</p>
               <p>If the Owner of the Cattel <note place="margin">Idem ibid. &amp; Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 207. b.</note> tender amends to him that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, and he refuſe it, yet the Owner may not take his Cattel out of the Pound; for if he do, a <hi>Parco fracto</hi> lieth againſt him.</p>
               <p>But after ſuch tender he may <note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:60010:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:60010:60"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:60010:61"/>
ſue out a Replevin, to have them out; and if it appear, when they come to a Trial, to the Jury that the Tender was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, then the Owner ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Dammages in the Reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin againſt him that diſtrained, for detaining the goods; and if on the contrary it appear that the Tender was not ſufficient, then the Avowant, that is he that diſtrained, ſhall have ſuch Amends as the Jury ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs.</p>
               <p>If after ſuch Amends tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> f. 207. b.</note> the Cattel die in ſuch Pound overt, the Owner ſhall be at the loſs, by reaſon of the wrong done at the beginning, to ſee that they ſhall have meat ſo long as they be in Pound.</p>
               <p>But if the Owner of the Cattel procure a Replevin to <note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> deliver them, and he that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained reſiſts it, and will not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60010:61"/>
deliver them; in this caſe, if they die after for want of meat, it is at the peril of him that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, and the owner ſhall recover Dammages againſt him in an action upon the Statute, for diſobeying of the King's Writ.</p>
               <p>If I ſend my Servant to take <note place="margin">Compleat Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, p. 193. 21 F. 4. f. 19. Kitchin, f. 208. b.</note> a Diſtreſs for a Rent or Service, who puts it in the Pound, if the Owner of the Beaſts or a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger take them out, I ſhall have a <hi>Parco fracto;</hi> for it is my Pound, and not my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant's.</p>
               <p>If I impound Cattel taken <note place="margin">Idem ibidem. F. N. B. 100. Finch, l. 4. c. 16. p. 310.</note> upon a Diſtreſs in a friend's Cloſe with his licence, and the Owner of the Cattel take them out; in this caſe I ſhall have a <hi>Parco fracto,</hi> and my friend an Action of Treſpaſs for breaking his Cloſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:60010:62"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Who may take a Diſtreſs, and for what cauſe, and when, and where.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Man may diſtrain of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right for Rent-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, <note place="margin">Co. 1 part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. 204. b. 205. a. 30 Aſſ. pl. 8 17 E. 3. 7 Co. lib. 4. f. 73. Philipps pr. of Law, p. 26. Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 9.</note> Homage, Fealty, Eſcuage, Suit of Court, &amp;c. or for a Rent reſerved upon a Gift in Tail, Leaſe for Life, Years, or at Will, though there be no clauſe of Diſtreſs in the Leaſe.</p>
               <p>But for Debt, Accompt, <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ib.</note> Treſpaſs, Reparations, &amp;c. a man may not diſtrain.</p>
               <p>It is a Maxime in Law, that <note place="margin">20 E. 3. Avowry 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. 25 H. 6.37. Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. fo. 230, &amp; 238. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 96. a Brit. f. 100.</note> no Diſtreſs can be taken for any Services that are not put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to certainty, nor can be reduced to any certainty; for <hi>id certum eſt quod certum reddi poteſt,</hi> for <hi>oportet quòd certa res deduca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Judicium:</hi> and upon
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60010:62"/>
the Avowry Dammages cannot be recovered for that which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath certainty nor can be reduced to certainty.</p>
               <p>And yet in ſome caſes there may be a certainty in an incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty: <note place="margin">7 F. 3.38. &amp; Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> as a man may hold of his Lord to ſhear all his Sheep depaſturing within the Lord's Mannor; and this is certain enough, although the Lord hath ſometimes a greater number and ſometimes a leſſer number there; for this incertainty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reduced to the Mannor, which is certain, the Lord may diſtrain for this incertainty: <hi>&amp; ſic de ſimilibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Diſtreſs is inſeparably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 150. b. 151. b.</note> to every Service that may be reduced to certainty, as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>A man may not diſtrain for <note place="margin">10 E. 3 Avowry 137. 11 H. 7.5. Co. on Lit. f. 47. b. &amp; 142. a.</note> Rent after the Leaſe is ended, nor out of his Fee, except in ſome ſpecial caſes, nor in the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60010:63"/>
Night, unleſs it be Dammage-feaſant.</p>
               <p>The Executors or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators of him which had Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farm <note place="margin">Noye's Max. p. 45. Vide Raſtal T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. 32 H. 8.37. c. Wing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te's Abridgment of the Stat. p. 407, &amp; 408. Co. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Lit f. 162. a. &amp; Co. 4 l. f. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in Ognell's caſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</note> in Fee, in Fee-Tail, or for Life, may either have an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Debt againſt the Tenant that ſhould pay it, or diſtrain for it: and ſo may the Husband after the death of his Wife, his Executors or Adminiſtrators, and he which hath Rent for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other's Life for the Arrearages after his Death.</p>
               <p>If a man put Cattel into my <note place="margin">Noye's Maximes, p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Paſture for a week, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I give him notice that I will keep them no longer, and he will not fetch them away; I then may diſtrain them Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-feaſant.</p>
               <p>If a man take Cattel Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage-feaſant, <note place="margin">2 E. 3. Reſcous 12. Co. 1 part of Inſt. f. 161. a. Compl. Att. p. 196.</note> and as he is dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them to the Pound, they run into the Owner's houſe, who refuſes to let them out
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60010:63"/>
again; here he that diſtrains may have a Writ of Reſcous againſt the Owner for ſo doing.</p>
               <p>If the Lord come to diſtrain, <note place="margin">Noye's Max. p. 46. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 161. a. 6 R. 2. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. 11. 11 H. 7.4. 21 H. 7.40. Co. 9. l. f. 22 in caſe de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowry, &amp; Terms of the Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. <hi>Diſtreſs.</hi> 44 F. 3. f. 20. &amp; F. N. B. 102.</note> and ſee the Cattel, and the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee or his Servants drive the Beaſts out of his Fee; here the Lord cannot have Reſcous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had not the poſſeſſion, but he may follow and diſtrain them in another's ground, but not for Dammage-feaſant, for they muſt be Dammage-feaſant at the time of the taking.</p>
               <p>If a man take a Diſtreſs of <note place="margin">Clayton's Rep. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4. pl. 111.</note> goods, and ſhews no cauſe for what, if they be put in an houſe, the Owner may break the houſe and take them out.</p>
               <p>If a Diſtreſs be taken of <note place="margin">4 E. 6. Tit. <hi>Diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> 74. F. N. B. 100. E. Co on Lit. f. 47. b. 9 E. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. f. 35. 5 F. 4. f. 7. per Danby. 40 F. 3. f. 33.</note> goods without cauſe, the Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner may Reſcue; but if they be impounded, he cannot break<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Pound and take them out, becauſe they are then in the Cuſtody of the Law.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:60010:64"/>
If a man diſtrain Cattel for <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 3 E. 3 Tit. Tranſ. 11. &amp; 34 H. 6.18.</note> Dammage-feaſant, and put them in the Pound, and the Owner that had Common there maketh freſh Suit, and finds the Door unlocked; he may then take them out: but if it be locked, he cannot juſtifie to take them out.</p>
               <p>If Beaſts driven by the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way eſcape into another man's <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l 1. c. 16 Cowell's Inſt. p. 231.</note> Corn, he that driveth them is no Treſpaſſer by his Entry to fetch them out again.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Feoffment reſerving a Rent, he cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. c. 9.</note> without a Clauſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs; and if the Feoffment be not by Indenture, the Reſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is void in Law: like Law where a particular Eſtate is made reſerving a Rent, the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der over in Fee.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for Life grant his <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid.</note> whole Eſtate reſerving a Rent, the Reſervation is void, if it be
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:60010:64"/>
not by Deed Indented, and without a Clauſe of Diſtreſs it is a Rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeck, and he cannot diſtrain.</p>
               <p>For an Amercement in a <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid. 10 H. 7. f. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4 E. 2. and 19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. Avowry 221.</note> Leet the Lord may diſtrain; and though the Diſtreſs be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the High-way, yet in this caſe it is lawful.</p>
               <p>A man cannot diſtrain for an Amercement in a Court Baron, <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid. 47 E. 3. f. 12. Vide Kitchin, f. 61. b. Hughes's gr. Abr. 1 par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, p. 721. Co. 10.</note> nor for an Amercement in the Leet in a place ſeiſed into the King's hands for the King's Debt, for it is for that time pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileged.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made at <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elmas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid. &amp; Vide Co. on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Lit. fo. 47. b.</note> for a year, rendring Rent at the <hi>Annunciation</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas,</hi> the Leſſor may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain at the <hi>Annunciation,</hi> but not at <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> becauſe the term is expired.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for another's Life make a Leaſe for Years reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid. Vide Perkins, 691, 692.</note> Rent, and <hi>Ceſtui que vie</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:60010:65"/>
dieth; in this caſe Tenant <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>autre vie</hi> cannot diſtrain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Reverſion is determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>If a Town be Amerced, and the Neighbours by aſſent aſſeſs a <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 9.</note> certain Summ upon every Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant, and it is agreed, that if it be not pay'd by ſuch a day, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perſons thereto appointed ſhall diſtrain; ſuch Diſtreſs is lawful.</p>
               <p>Lord and Tenant by Fealty <note place="margin">Dr &amp; Stud. ibid. 12 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.11. 9 E. 3. 1 Vide l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. of Ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 44 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e 20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kins, 113.</note> and Rent, the Lord grants the Fealty reſerving the Rent, and the Tenant attorns; the Lord cannot now diſtrain for the Rent, for it is now made Seck.</p>
               <p>But if a man make a Gift in Tail reſerving Fealty and Rent, <note place="margin">Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid.</note> and after grants the Fealty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Rent and Reverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; here he may diſtrain for the Rent, for the Fealty is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to the Reverſion, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be granted without it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:60010:65"/>
For Herriot-Service the Lord may diſtrain, but for Herriot-Cuſtome he muſt ſeiſe, and not diſtrain.</p>
               <p>For Rent granted upon Egal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of partition or of Dower, the <note place="margin">21 H. 6.7. &amp; Dr. &amp; Stud. ibid.</note> party may diſtrain.</p>
               <p>If a man break the Pound, and take out his goods, he that <note place="margin">34 H. 6.18. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 47. b. Vid. Comp. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. p. 192.</note> diſtrained may have a <hi>Parco fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto</hi> againſt him, and may alſo take the goods again whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he finds them, and put them in the Pound again.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant foreſtall the <note place="margin">Co. on Lit. f. 153. b. &amp; f. 161. b. Fleta, l. 1. c. 42. Vide 29. Aſſ. 49. Noye's Max. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 46.</note> way with force and armes, and threaten in ſuch manner that the Lord dares not come to diſtrain or demand the Rent, or if there be no Diſtreſs on the ground, nor none ready to pay the Rent; then in this caſe the Lord may have a W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it of <hi>Novel Diſſeiſin</hi> againſt the Tenant, and recover his Rent and Arrearages: and if the Rent be behind another
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60010:66"/>
time, he may have a Rediſſeiſin, and recover double Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</p>
               <p>If a man take a Diſtreſs he <note place="margin">M. 7 Jac. in C. B. More and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham's caſe. Owen's Rep. f. 123. Vide in Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw and Gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard's caſe, Hil. 3 Jac. in B. R. Rot. 1070. Cro. Rep. 1 part, fo. 147.</note> may not work it, for he hath neither property nor poſſeſſion <hi>in Jure.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Reſcous, where it ſhall be lawful.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REſcous</hi> is an old <hi>French</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 160. b.</note> word coming from <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourrer (id eſt) Recuperare,</hi> that is, to take from, or reſcue, or recover; and is a taking away or ſetting at liberty againſt Law a Diſtreſs taken, or a perſon ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted by the Proceſs or Courſe of Law.</p>
               <p>And all is one as to the point <note place="margin">Co. ibid. F. N. B. 101. c. &amp; 102. f.</note>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:60010:66"/>
of the Diſſeiſin, to reſcue the <note place="margin">Keilway 20. 6 H. 6. Diſſeiſſ. 9. 21 H. 7. 40. a. Finch, l. 4. c. 16. &amp; p. 310.</note> Diſtreſs after it is taken, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand to reſiſt and withſtand the taking of it; but yet it is no Reſcous until it be diſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>If the Lord diſtrain when <note place="margin">See in Bevil's ca. Co. 4. l. f. 11. 61 R. 2. Reſcous 10.</note> there is no Rent arrear, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant may make Reſcous and hinder.</p>
               <p>Or if the Lord come to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, and the Tenant tender <note place="margin">7 E. 4.24. &amp; Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 160. b.</note> the Rent to him, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Lord will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain, then the Tenant may make Reſcous.</p>
               <p>If the Rent be behind, and the Lord diſtrain the Cattel of <note place="margin">Co. ibid. 17 E. 3. 43. Vide Marlbr. ca. 15. 52 H. 3. Wingate's Abr. Stat. p. 132. See Raſtall Tit. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes 5. Ferrer's <hi>Magn. Charta,</hi> f. 25. b.</note> the Tenant in the High-way within his Fee, the Tenant may make Reſcous; for no man may diſtrain in the High-way, except the King and his Officers having ſpecial Authority.</p>
               <p>If the Lord will diſtrain <hi>Ave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Carucae,</hi> goods of the <note place="margin">Co. on Lit. f. 161.2.</note>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60010:67"/>
Plough, where there is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Diſtreſs to be taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <note place="margin">Raſtall Tit. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes 10. &amp; ſee Wingate's Abr. Sta. p. 132. Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer's <hi>Mag. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> f. 122. b.</note> or if the Lord diſtrain any thing that is not diſtrainable ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Common Law or by any Statute, the Tenant may make Reſcous.</p>
               <p>If the Lord diſtrain out of his Fee in Lands not holden of <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 161. a.</note> him, the Tenant may make Reſcous, unleſs it be in ſome ſpecial caſes. See after in Ch. 10.</p>
               <p>If the Lord come to diſtrain <note place="margin">Co. ibid. Comp. Att. p. 196. Co. 9. l. f. 22. in the caſe of Avowry. 6 R. 2. Reſc. 11.44 E. 3.20. Hughes's gr. Ab. 1 part, p. 717. c. 21. F. N. B. 102. g. 21 H. 7. f. 40. Kitchin, f. 52. b.</note> Cattel which he ſeeth then within his Fee, and the Tenant, or any other, to prevent the Lord to diſtrain, drive the Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel out of the Fee of the Lord into ſome other place, yet may the Lord freſhly follow, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the Cattel, and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant cannot make Reſcous; for in judgment of Law the Diſtreſs is taken within his Fee, and ſo ſhall the Writ of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcous ſuppoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:60010:67"/>
But if the Lord coming to diſtrain had no view of the Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 161. a. &amp; Compl. Att. p. 196. Vide. Hughes's gr. Ab. 1 part, p. 717. c. 21.</note> within his Fee, though the Tenant drive them off purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or if the Cattel of themſelves after the view go out of the Fee, or if the Tenant after the view removeth them for any other cauſe then to prevent the Lord of his Diſtreſs; then can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not the Lord diſtrain them out of his Fee, for if he do, the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant may Reſcue.</p>
               <p>If a man come to diſtrain for Dammage-feaſant, and ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 161. a. 161.4. 10.2 E 2. Avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry 182. Co. 9. l. f. 22. in Caſe de Avowry. Noye's Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p. 46.</note> Beaſts in his Soil, and the Owner chaſes them out of purpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Diſtreſs taken, the Owner of the Soil cannot fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and take them; for if he do, the Owner of the Cattel may reſcue them: for they muſt be Dammage-feaſant at the time of the Diſtreſs taken, and the Owner of the Soil is left to his Action of Treſpaſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:60010:68"/>
If the Tenant lock up his <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 10 E. 3.9.49 E. 3.14.7 E. 3.3.11 H. 7. 28. 8 Aſſ. 18. 10 E. 4.2.</note> Gates, and incloſe his grounds, ſo that the Lord cannot come to diſtrain, this is a Diſſeiſin, if the Lord have had actual poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and the Rent is behind; for the Lord cannot break open the Incloſures to take a Diſtreſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Of Replevins, when and where to be ſued out.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REplegiare</hi> is compounded of <hi>Re</hi> and <hi>Plegiare,</hi> as much <note place="margin">Co 1 part Inſt. f. 145. b.</note> as to ſay to deliver upon Pledges or Sureties.</p>
               <p>Where goods are diſtrained and impounded, the Owner of <note place="margin">Co. ibid Vide Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, l. 2. c. 40. &amp; Glanvill, l. 12. c. 12.</note> the goods may have a Writ <hi>De Replegiari facias,</hi> whereby the Sheriff is commanded, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Pledges of proſecuting, to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60010:68"/>
re<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> deliver the goods diſtrain'd to the Owner; and this is by the Common Law.</p>
               <p>But the quickeſt way is to <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Weſtmin. 2. c. 2. Vide Ferrer's <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> f. 60. Raſtal Tit. Replevin 2. &amp; Wingate's Abr. Stat. p. 409. Compl. Att. p. 127.</note> complain to ſome of the Sheriffs Deputies in the Country, who keep a Seal for that purpoſe, and they will grant a Replevin, and muſt take <hi>Plegii de Retorno ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendo,</hi> that is to deliver the goods again to the party that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, if the action be found againſt him that Replevieth; and this is by the Statute.</p>
               <p>By the Stat. 1, 2 <hi>P. M.</hi> C. 12. <note place="margin">Wingate's Abr. p. 133. Raſt. Tit. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes 11. Vide Sheppard's Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of County Judicatures, p. 47.</note> every Sheriff is at his firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-day, or within two Months after he receives his Patent, to depute and proclaim in his Shire-Town 4 Deputies to make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevins, not dwelling above 12 Miles diſtant one from another; if he fails herein, he forfeits 5 pound every Moneth they are wanting, to be divided between the King and the Proſecutor.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:60010:69"/>
If the Lord carry the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs <note place="margin">Compl. Att. p. 125, 126. Ferrer's <hi>Ma. Charta,</hi> f. 37. Weſtm. 1. <hi>c.</hi> 17. Vide Raſtall Tit. Diſtreſſes 7. &amp; Wingate's Abr. p. 133. Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>Diſtreſs.</hi> Vide Sheppard's Sur. of County Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures, p. 49.</note> to a Hold or out of the County, ſo that the Sheriff cannot make Deliverance upon the Replevin, then the party upon the Sheriff's return of the Replevin may have a Writ of <hi>Withernam</hi> directed to the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff, to take as many of the Lord's Beaſts or as much goods in his keeping till he have made deliverance of the firſt Diſtreſs; and if the Beaſts or goods be conveyed to a Fort or Caſtle, the Sheriff may take with him the Power of the County, and beat down the Caſtle.</p>
               <p>If it be in a Franchiſe or Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liwick, <note place="margin">Comp. Att. p. 127. Vide Marlb. c. 21. Ferrer's <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> f 27. &amp; Raſtall Repl. 1.</note> the party ſhall have a Replevin of the Sheriff, directed to the Bailiff, to deliver them upon Pledges as before.</p>
               <p>It is a general Rule, that the Plaintiff in the Replevin muſt <note place="margin">3 E. 3.74.6 H. 4.2. &amp; 39.9 H. 6. 39. 20 H. 6. 19. 30 E. 3.22. 31 E. 3. Repl. 35. Co 1 part Inſt. f. 145. b.</note> have the property of the goods in him at the time of the taking;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60010:69"/>
for if the Defendant (that is he that diſtrained) claim property, the Sheriff cannot grant a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevin upon Complaint to him made; for it is a Rule in Law, that Property muſt be tried by Writ.</p>
               <p>And therefore in this caſe the <note place="margin">31 H. 6. <hi>Prop. pro-banda</hi> 5.1. E. 4.9. 21 E. 4.64, &amp; 66. 2 El. Dyer 173. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 145. b. Vide Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard's Surv. of County Judic. p. 50, 51, &amp; 52.</note> Plaintiff (that is he that ſues out the Replevin) may have a Writ <hi>De proprietate probanda</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Sheriff, to try the Property; and if it be found for the Plaintiff, then the Sheriff to make Deliverance, and if for the Defendant, the Sheriff can proceed no farther; unleſs the Plaintiff get a <hi>Replegiari facias</hi> to the Sheriff; and then, though he return the property, &amp;c. yet it ſhall proceed in the Common Pleas, where the property ſhall be put in iſſue, and finally tried.</p>
               <p>The Sheriff may take a Plaint upon the Stat. <hi>Marlebr.</hi> out of <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> his County, and make Reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60010:70"/>
preſently; for it ſhould be inconvenient for the Owner to forbear his Cattel till the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-day.</p>
               <p>If he that diſtrained the Beaſts ſee cauſe, he may have a Writ of <hi>Recordare,</hi> and ſo remove the Suit upon the Replevin out of the Sheriff's County-Court into the Comon-Pleas-Court; and if the Plaintiff declare not, he that diſtrained may have a <hi>Retorno habendo;</hi> and if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare not ſtill, then the Avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſhall have a Writ to enquire of Dammages.</p>
               <p>Note, there be two kinds of <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 145. b. 42 E. 3. 18. 11 H. 4. 17. 7 H. 4.17. 48 E. 3. 20. Vide Sheppard's Survey of County Judicatures, p. 46.</note> Properties; a general proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which every abſolute Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath, and a ſpecial property, as goods pledged, or taken to manure his Lands, or the like: and of both theſe a Replevin doth lie.</p>
               <p>It is to be noted, that a man <note place="margin">5 E. 3.38. 11 H. 4. 4. 17 E. 2 <hi>Prop. prob.</hi> 6. Co. 1 part</note> cannot claim property by his
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60010:70"/>
Bailiff or Servant; and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <note place="margin">Inſt. f. 145. b. Philipps Prin. of Law, p. 69. Vide Sheppard's Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey of County Judicatures, p. 52 &amp; 53.</note> is, for that if the Claim fall out to be falſe, he ſhall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for his contempt, which the Lord cannot be, unleſs he make Claim himſelf; for <hi>Nemo punitur pro alieno Delicto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a man by his Deed grant <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Bract. l. 4. f. 233. a b. 31 E. 3. Gage Deliver. 5.</note> a Rent with Clauſe of Diſtreſs, and grant farther that he ſhall keep the goods diſtrained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gages and Pledges until the Rent be pay'd, yet ſhall the Sheriff Replevie the goods diſtrained; for it is againſt the nature of ſuch a Diſtreſs to be Irrepleviable, and by ſuch an Intention the Current of Replevins ſhould be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, to the hindrance of the Commonwealth.</p>
               <p>If the Beaſts of divers ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 145. b. 28 E. 3.92. 3 H. 4. 12. 34 H. 6. 37. Sheppard's Sur. of County Judicatures, p. 46 47, &amp; 52.</note> men be diſtrained, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not join in a Replevin, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one muſt have a ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevin; for in a Replevin it is
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60010:71"/>
a good Plea to ſay that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty is to the Plaintiff and to a Stranger, and where there be two Plaintiffs, that the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is to one of them.</p>
               <p>The Tenant ſhall have a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevin <note place="margin">F. N. B. 69. b. 4 H. 7.40. 11 H. 7. 10. Compl. Att. p. 131. &amp; Philipps Pr. of Law, p. 143. Finch, l. 1. c. 3. p. 46.</note> againſt the Lord that did wrongfully diſtrain, though the Beaſts be come back again to the Owner, becauſe he can have no Action of Treſpaſs againſt the Lord.</p>
               <p>A Replevin ought to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <note place="margin">Tr. 23 Car. in B. R. Regeſt. Practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, p. 193.</note> in ſetting forth the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and kindes of the Cattel di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, or elſe it is not good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:60010:71"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of Avowries, a word or two briefly concerning the ſame.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Avowry</hi> is where one taketh <note place="margin">Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowry.</hi>
                  </note> a Diſtreſs for Rent or other thing, and the Owner of the goods ſueth out a Replevin, then he that taketh the Diſtreſs ſhall juſtifie in his Plea for what cauſe he took it; and if he took it in his own Right, he muſt ſhew that, and ſo avow the taking, and that is called his Avowrie.</p>
               <p>But if he took the Diſtreſs <note place="margin">Terms of the Law, verb. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowry.</hi>
                  </note> in or for the Right of another, then when he hath ſhewed the cauſe, he muſt make Conuſance of the taking, as Bailiff or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to him in whoſe Right he took it.</p>
               <p>In Avowrie if the Plaintiff <note place="margin">Raſtall Tit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowry, and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate's Abr. p 34</note>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:60010:72"/>
be Non-ſuit, or otherwiſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">Vide Tr. 15 Car. B. R. Tintnye &amp; James's Caſe, in Winche's Rep. f. 30, &amp; 31. &amp; in Cro. 1 part, 358, &amp; 385. the ſame caſe, where there is excellent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter about Avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> or overthrown, then the Avowants ſhall recover their Dammages and Coſts againſt the ſaid Plaintiffs, as the ſame Plaintiffs ſhould have done or had if they had recovered in the Replevin or Second Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance found againſt the ſaid A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowants.</p>
               <p>The Lord may avow the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">Raſtall and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 269. b.</note> a Diſtreſs as in Lands hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of him within his Fee, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naming any perſon in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and this is by the Statute of the 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. c. 19.</p>
               <p>But by the Common Law they could not do this, but were forced to avow upon a perſon in certain, which proved often ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prejudicial to the Lords; for by the ſecret Fines, Recoveries, Grants and Feoffments which the Tenants made purpoſely to defraud their Lords, they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon were put from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60010:72"/>
of their Tenants, upon whom by order of Law they ſhould make their Avowry, and ſo to prevent this Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the ſaid Statute was made.</p>
               <p>But the Lord may avow ſtill <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Vide Mich. 6 Jac. Co. 8. l. Sir Will. Foſter's caſe. 32 H. 8. ch. 2. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall Tit. Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 3. &amp; Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate's Abr. p. 295.</note> by the Common Law if he will: and although he do avow by the Statute upon the Lands ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, as in Lands, &amp;c. within his Fee or Seigniory, yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he muſt alledg Seiſin by the hands of ſome particular Tenant in certain within 40 years.</p>
               <p>In an Avowrie made accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">Raſtall Tit. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowry; &amp; Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate's Abr. p. 34.</note> to the Statute, every Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff in the Replevin or Second Deliverance, be he Termor or other, may have every Anſwer to the Avowrie that is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and alſo have Aid and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other Advantage in Law, Diſclaimer onely excepted: for diſclaim he cannot, becauſe the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60010:73"/>
Avowry is made upon no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon certain.</p>
               <p>If the Lord come to diſtrain, and the Tenant chaſe his Beaſts <note place="margin">Co. 9. l. in Caſe de Avowry, f. 22.</note> which were within the Lord's view out of the Land holden, &amp;c. yet if the Lord freſhly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and take them, although it be out of his Fee and Seigniorie, he may by the Equity of the Statute avow the taking as in Lands holden of him within his Fee and Seigniory.</p>
               <p>If there be Lord and Tenant, <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 269. b. &amp; ſee Co. 3 l. f. 65, &amp; 66. in Pennant's caſe.</note> and the Rent is behind for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers years, and the Tenant makes a Feoffment in Fee, if the Lord accept the Service or Rent of the Feoffee due in his time, he ſhall loſe the Arrearages due in the time of the Feoffor; for after ſuch acceptance he ſhall not avow upon the Feoffor, nor upon the Feoffee for the Arrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages in the time of the Feoffor: But if the Feoffor dieth, albeit
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:60010:73"/>
the Lord accept the Rent or Service by the hands of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offee due in his time, yet he ſhall not loſe the Arrearages; for now the Law compelleth him to avow upon the Feoffee, and that which the Law compelleth him unto ſhall not prejudice him.</p>
               <p>There are four manner of <note place="margin">Vide Aiſcough's caſe 9 Jac. Co. 9. l. f. 135, &amp; 136.20 H. 6.9. 26 H. 6. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowr. 17. 9 Eliz. Dyer 257.20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. Avowry 131.5 H. 7.11.</note> Avowries.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Upon his very Tenant.</item>
                  <item>2. Upon his very Tenant by the manner, where the Tenant had but a particular Eſtate.</item>
                  <item>3. Upon his Tenant by the manner, where the Lord had but a particular Eſtate. And theſe 3 are by the Common Law.</item>
                  <item>4. Upon the matter in the Land as within his Fee; and this is by the Statute, and the ſafeſt way.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:60010:74"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of Waſte: What ſhall be Waſte in Houſes, Gardens, Woods, Paſtures, &amp;c. and what not.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF Leſſee for Life, Years, in <note place="margin">34 F. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Waſte 143. Vide 10 H. 7. f. 2. b. 12 H. 4. f. 4. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a. Vide Hern's Law of Conv. p. 51.</note> Dower, &amp;c. pull or proſtrate down the Houſes, or ſuffer them to be uncovered, whereby the Sparrs or Rafters, Planchers or other Timber of the Houſes are rotten, this is Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Houſe be uncovered when the Tenant cometh in, it <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Herne's Law of Conv. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> is no Waſte in the Tenant, if he ſuffer the ſame to fall down.</p>
               <p>But although the Houſe be <note place="margin">40 Aſſ. pl. 22. 23 H. 6.24. 29 E. 3. 33. Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Compl. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 166. Herne, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> uncovered and ruinous at the time of the Tenant's coming in, ye if he pull it down, it is Waſte, unleſs he do build it again.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:60010:74"/>
If Glaſs-windows (though <note place="margin">Vide Co. 4. l. f. 63. in Harlacken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den's caſe. Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn's Wills 3 par. ſect. 6. f. 165. &amp; Herne, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> glaſed by the Tenant himſelf) be broken down or carried away, it is Waſte; for the Glaſs is part of the Houſe.</p>
               <p>And ſo it is of Wainſcoat, <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 35. a. Vide Keil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, f 88. &amp; Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lackenden's caſe, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 22 H. 6. 18.22 E. 4.18. Swinburn, <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Compl. Att. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> whether it be fixed to the Walls or Poſts of the Houſe with great Nailes or little Nailes, Screws or Pins, it is all one, if it be fixed to the Free-hold once, it is Waſte to take it away again.</p>
               <p>The ſame Law of Benches, <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a. 10 El Dyer 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. 42 E. 3. f. 6. Noye's Maximes, p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Doors, Windows, Furnaces and the like, annexed or fixed to the Houſe, either by him in the Reverſion or the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>The Raſing of a new Frame of a Houſe which was never <note place="margin">40 Aſſ. pl. 22. Pr. Waſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>17. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin. f. 242. b.</note> covered, is no Waſte.</p>
               <p>The Houſe uncovered by <note place="margin">12 H 4. f. 4. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 241. b Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 19 E. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. Herne's Law of Convey p. 52.</note> ſudden Tempeſt or otherwiſe, it is no Waſte in the Tenant if he let it lie ſo, till the main
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60010:75"/>
Timber be rotten; and then he ſhall be puniſhed in Waſte, for not repairing it in time.</p>
               <p>If the Houſe fall by ſudden Tempeſt, or be burnt by Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in Co. 4. l. f. 63. Harlackenden's caſe. Dr. &amp; St. l. 2. c. 4.</note> or proſtrated by Enemies, or the like, without any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault of the Tenant, or was Ruinous at his coming in and fall down, this is no Waſte.</p>
               <p>And the Tenant may build the ſame again with ſuch mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials <note place="margin">Co <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 43 E. 3.6.11 H. 4.32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1 H. 6.18. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 52.</note> as remain, and with other Timber growing upon the ground, (which he may take) for his habitation; but he muſt not make the Houſe larger then it was, for if he do, he is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in Waſte.</p>
               <p>Though there be no Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 44 E. 3.21.38 Aſſ. pl. 1. Com. Att. p. 166. Herne's Law of Conv p. 51.</note> growing upon the ground, yet the Tenant at his peril muſt keep the Houſes from waſting.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant build a new <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Kitchin, f. 242. a. 42 E. 3.21. 12 H. 4. f. 6.17 E. 2. Waſt 118.</note> Houſe where none was before, it is Waſte; and if he ſuffer it to
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:60010:75"/>
be waſted, it is a new Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant either doe or <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a. 40 E. 3. f. 6. 38 Aſſ. pl. 1. Vide Kitchin, f. 242. a. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 51, &amp; 52.</note> ſuffer Waſte to be done in the Houſes, yet if he repair them before any Action brought, he is clear; but he cannot plead <hi>quòd non fecit vaſtum,</hi> but the ſpecial matter.</p>
               <p>The pulling down of a Stone-wall <note place="margin">Kitchin, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 10 H. 7. f. 2. b. Com. Att. p. 166.</note> or Mud-wall of an Houſe is Waſte.</p>
               <p>A Wall uncovered when the <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Tenant comes in, is no Waſte if he ſuffer it to decay.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant of a Dove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, <note place="margin">Brit. f. 134.5 R. 2. Waſt 97. Pl. Com. 322. Hobart's Rep. f. 234. Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Hern's Law of Conv. p. 52.</note> Park, Warren, Vinary, Eſtangues, &amp;c. do take ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as ſuch ſufficient ſtore be not left as he found when he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, this is Waſte; and to ſuffer the Pale to decay, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Deer are diſperſed, is Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant ſuffer the <note place="margin">F. N. B. 59. k. Kitchin, f. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. b.</note> Houſes to be waſted, and then fell Timber to repair them,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:60010:76"/>
this is a double Waſte.</p>
               <p>If a Termor fix a Furnace, and not to the Walls nor Poſts <note place="margin">21 H. 7 f. 26. <hi>per</hi> Kingſmil.</note> of the Houſe, if he take it away within his term, it is no Waſte, for the Houſe is not impai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Fee fix a Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace <note place="margin">Kitchin <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</hi>
                  </note> or Fatt in the middle of the Houſe, the Heir ſhall have it, and not the Executors.</p>
               <p>If an Houſe fall by a great <note place="margin">34 E. 3. f. 3. b. 11 H. 4. f. 21.</note> Wind or Tempeſt, the Leſſor ſhall have the Timber, for it is no Waſte, and the Leſſee is not bound to re-edifie it.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant take away a Lead or Fatts fixed to the Houſe, it is Waſte.</p>
               <p>If a Stable be ruinous at the <note place="margin">11 H. 4. f. 32. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f 242. b.</note> time of the Leaſe made and fall, the Tenant may cut down Trees to make a new one; but if there were none there before, it is Waſte if he cut Trees to build one.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:60010:76"/>
The Tenant may cut Trees <note place="margin">Kitchin <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</hi> Fitz. 59. k.</note> to amend the Houſe and make Reparations; but where it is in decay through his own Default, there if he cut Trees to repair it, it is Waſte.</p>
               <p>It is to be obſerved, that there <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a. Vid. Herne's Law of Convey. p. 52.</note> is Waſte, Deſtruction and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile. Waſte properly is in Houſes, Gardens and Timber-Trees, (viz. Oak, Aſh and Elm, and theſe are Timber in all places) either by cutting of them down, or lopping and top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping them, or doing any act whereby the Timber may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay.</p>
               <p>Alſo in Countries where <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Herne <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Timber is ſcant, and Beeches or the like are converted to building for the habitation of man, or the like, they then are alſo accounted Timber, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them by the Tenant is Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant cut down <note place="margin">22 H. 6.12. a. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> N. B. 59. m. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:60010:77"/>
Timber-Trees as is afore ſaid, or ſuch as are accounted Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, it is Waſte; and if he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the young germens to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, this is Deſtruction, and puniſhable in Waſte alſo.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant cut down Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-wood, (as he may by Law) <note place="margin">20 E. 3. Waſt 32. 10 H. 7.2.42. E. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. b. 5 E 4. 100. 41 E. 3. Waſt 82. 12 E. 4. 1. &amp; Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a.</note> yet if he ſuffer the young ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens to be deſtroyed, or ſtub up the ſame by the Roots, ſo that it can grow no more, this is Waſte.</p>
               <p>Cutting down of Willows, <note place="margin">40 E. 3. f. 15. b. 4 E. 6. Waſte, Br. 136. Kitchin f. 243. a. Co. <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</hi> Comp Att. p. 165. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 52.</note> Beech, Birch, Aſpe, Maple or the like, ſtanding and grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Defence and within the view of the Houſe, is Waſte.</p>
               <p>Beech of the age of 20 years, nor under 20 years, may <note place="margin">Temps H. 8. Br Waſte 184.</note> not be cut by Tenant for Life or Years, for it is Waſte, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be in ſome Countries where there is plenty of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:60010:77"/>
A man cannot aſſign Waſte <note place="margin">13 H. 7. f. 21.</note> in the cutting of Beeches of the age of 7 or 8 years.</p>
               <p>Cutting of Haſels which grow not under the great Trees, <note place="margin">40 E. 3 f. 25. b. 10 H. 7. f. 2. F. N. B. 60. c. Kitchin, f. 243. a.</note> but in a quarter of the Wood by themſelves, is Waſte.</p>
               <p>If there be a Quick-ſet-Eence of White-thorn, and <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſtit. f. 53. a. 46 E. 3. f. 17. 9 H. 6. f. 10.12 H. 8.1. Kitchin, f. 244<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a.</note> the Tenant ſtubs it up, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it to be deſtroyed, it is Waſte.</p>
               <p>The Cutting of dead Wood <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá,</hi> &amp; Kitchin <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> F. N. B. 59. m. 16 El. Dyer 332.</note> which is dry and hollow, and neither bears Fruit nor Leaves in Summer, is no Waſte.</p>
               <p>The Tenant may take ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. b.</note> Wood to repair the Walls, Pales, Fences, Hedges and Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as he found them; but he can make no new ones but it will be Waſte.</p>
               <p>He may alſo take ſufficient Plough-bote, Houſe-bote, and Fire-bote, as is ſhewed before in Chap. 5. p. 91.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:60010:78"/>
If the Tenant cut down Trees <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 53. b. Compl. Att. p. 167. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 58.</note> for Reparations and ſell them, and after buieth them again and imploies them about neceſſary Reparations, yet it is Waſte by the Vendition, for he cannot ſell Trees, and with the mony cover the Houſe.</p>
               <p>Burning of the Houſe by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence <note place="margin">Co. ibid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; Herne <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> or miſchance is Waſte.</p>
               <p>A Termor may take Beech, <note place="margin">4 E. 6. Bro. Waſte 136.</note> Aſhes, and the like, which are well ſeaſonable, and have been uſed to be felled every 20, 16, 14, or 12 years, and it is no Waſte, for it is called <hi>Sylva caedua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Cutting of Beeches and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note place="margin">7 H. 6. f. 40. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 243. b.</note> them is Waſte; but the Termor may cut them to repair upon the ſame Land, but not to make Reparations upon other Lands.</p>
               <p>Cutting Beeches of 10 years old ſeaſonable for Houſe-bote, <note place="margin">11 H. 6 f. 1. Sed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide 4 E. 6. f. 136 Kitchin, f. 243. a.</note> is no Waſte; but where they
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:60010:78"/>
are of the age of 20 years, and fit for main Timber, that is Waſte.</p>
               <p>Where Oaks are cut, and <note place="margin">Kitchin, f. 243. b. 11 H. 6. f. 1. Com. Att. p. 167.</note> the young germens ſuffered to be eaten with Cattel, ſo that they will be but Shrubs, this is Waſte.</p>
               <p>One may aſſign Waſte in <note place="margin">22 H. 6. f. 14. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 243. b.</note> the cutting of 20 Oaks, and alſo in their Stocks, to wit in not ſpringing them again; for if they were ſaved, they would be Timber, and for that they are not ſaved, it is Waſte.</p>
               <p>A Termor may cut ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able wood, which is wont to be <note place="margin">F. N. B. fo. 59. m.</note> cut every 20 years, or within ſuch time.</p>
               <p>Cutting of White-thorn is <note place="margin">46 E. 3. f. 17. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 244. a.</note> Waſte, but not the cutting of Black-thorn.</p>
               <p>Where there is a Wood in <note place="margin">4 E. 6. Bro. Waſt 136.</note> which groweth nothing but Under-wood, the Termor can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not cut all; <hi>contrà</hi> of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:60010:79"/>
where Aſh, Beech, and other principal Trees grow amongſt them, for there he may cut all the Under-wood.</p>
               <p>Where Apple-trees are <note place="margin">7 H. 6. f. 40. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, f. 244. a.</note> blown down, and after become dead, the Tenant may cut them for Fewel.</p>
               <p>Cutting of Apple-trees, <note place="margin">Kitchin, ibid. 44 E. 3. f. 44. Compl. Att. p. 168.</note> though they ly all along on the ground, yet if they bear fruit, it is Waſte.</p>
               <p>Cutting of Damſin-trees is Waſte. <note place="margin">10 H. 7. f. 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If the Tenant cut down any of the Fruit-trees growing in <note place="margin">7 H. 6.38.44 E. 3. 44. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a.</note> the Garden or Orchard, it is Waſte.</p>
               <p>But if ſuch Trees grow in <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a. Vide Hern's Law of Conv. p. 52.</note> any place of the ground out of the Garden or Orchard, it is no Waſte if he cut them.</p>
               <p>Digging for Gravel, Lime, <note place="margin">Co. ibid. f. b. F. N. B. 59. n. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 53.</note> Clay, Brick-earth, Stones, or the like, is Waſte.</p>
               <p>And ſo it is if the Tenant dig
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:60010:79"/>
for Mines of Metall, Coals, &amp;c. <note place="margin">Idem ibid. 41 E. 3. Waſt 8. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart's Rep. f. 234. Herne <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> in the Earth, and not open at the time of the Leaſe made.</p>
               <p>But he may dig for Gravel or <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Com. Att. p. 168. Herne <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Clay for Reparations of the Houſe, and it is no Waſte.</p>
               <p>It is Waſte to ſuffer a Wall <note place="margin">Idem ibid. &amp; Brit. f. 168. b. 6. El. in Griffins' caſe.</note> of the Sea to be in decay, ſo as by the flowing and reflowing of the Sea the Meadow or Marſh is ſurrounded, whereby the ſame becomes unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but if it be ſuddenly by <note place="margin">6 El. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. N. B. 59. n.</note> the rage and violence of the Sea occaſioned by ſome Tempeſt or the like, without any default of the Tenant, this is no Waſte pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant repair not the <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 29 H. 8. Dyer 33. 22 H. 6.4.10 H. 7. 5. a. Kitchin, f. 241. b</note> Banks or Walls of Rivers or other Waters, whereby his Ground is ſurrounded, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ruſhy and unprofitable, this is Waſte.</p>
               <p>To ſuffer Paſture-ground to <note place="margin">Kitchin ibid. 20 H. 6. f. 1.</note> be ſurrounded with water, ſo
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:60010:80"/>
that it becomes ruſhy and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth, or Arable-Land to be ſurrounded, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remains but tough Clay, this is Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant convert Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-Land <note place="margin">Co 1 part Inſt. f. 53. b. 29 H. 8. Dyer 37. Hobart. Rep. f. 234. Vide Kitchin, f. 241. b. 10 H. 7.5. a. 44 E. 3.44. &amp; Com. Att. p. 168.</note> into Wood, or <hi>è con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſo,</hi> or Meadow into Arable, it is Waſte; for it doth not onely change the courſe of his Husbandry, but the proof of his Evidence.</p>
               <p>To ſuffer Arable-Land to lie <note place="margin">2 H. 6. f. 11. F. N. B. 59. n.</note> freſh, ſo that it is full of Thorns, is no Waſte.</p>
               <p>If a man leaſe his Lands in <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 54. b. 17 E. 3.7. 9 H. 6.66, F. N. B. 149. c. &amp; 59. n. Vide Hil, 15 Jac. in the Lord Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; Askwith's caſe. Hobart's Rep. f. 234. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 54, &amp; 55.</note> which are Mines of Coals or the like, without mentioning the Mines in the Leaſe, the Leſſee for ſuch Mines as are open at the time of the Leaſe made may dig lawfully, and take the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits thereof; but he may not dig for any new ones, it is Waſte.</p>
               <p>If there be open Mines, and <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:60010:80"/>
the Owner make a Leaſe of the <note place="margin">Vide Saunders's caſe, 41 El. in Co. B. Co. 5. l. f. 12. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 54, &amp; 55.</note> Land with the Mines therein, this ſhall extend to the open Mines onely, and not to any hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Mines: but if there be no open Mines, and the Leaſe is made of the Land together with all Mines therein, in this caſe the Tenant may dig for them, and enjoy the benefit thereof, otherwiſe the words ſhould be void.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to one of <note place="margin">17 E. 3. Tit. 101. Kitchin, f. 248. a.</note> Lands, to occupy the ſame af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beſt way he can, or to make his beſt profit of them, yet this ſhall be intended onely to be after ſuch manner as is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Right and Law; for in this caſe the Leſſee may not plow up Meadow, or pull down Houſes, &amp;c. for if he do, he ſhall be puniſhed in Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſee make the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanes <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. b.</note> or Tenants at VVill poor,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:60010:81"/>
where they were rich when he came in, whereby they depart from their Farms, this is Exile and puniſhable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Who are puniſhable in Waſte, and for what Waſte, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WAſte</hi> in <hi>Latine</hi> is called <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 52. b.</note> 
                  <hi>Vaſtum, à Vaſtando,</hi> from waſting and depopula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               <p>There are two kinds of <note place="margin">Idem, f. 53. a.</note> Waſte; that is to ſay, Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary or Actual Waſte, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive Waſte.</p>
               <p>An Action of Waſte lieth <note place="margin">Noye's Max. p. 33. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. a. &amp; 2 part Inſt. f. 302. Pl. Com. f. 467. b. 68. a. Philipps Pr. of Law, p. 32. Vid. <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> ch. 4. &amp; Stat. Glouc.</note> againſt Tenant by the Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Tenant for Life, for Years, or half a year, Tenant in Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Guardian in Chivalry, by
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:60010:81"/>
him that hath the Eſtate imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <note place="margin">ch. 5. Raſtal Waſt 1.4.5. &amp; Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate's Abr. Stat. p. 551, &amp; 552. 4 H. 6. f. 11. Kitchin, f. 338. a.</note> of Inheritance, for Waſte or Deſtruction in Houſes, Gardens, VVoods, Trees, Lands, Meadows, &amp;c. or in Exile of men, to the diſheriſon of him in the Reverſion or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, and they ſhall loſe the place waſted, and treble Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</p>
               <p>It doth not lie againſt Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian in Soccage, but an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 54. a. Ferrer's <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> f. 26. b.</note> of Account or Treſpaſs.</p>
               <p>Waſte lieth not againſt Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <note place="margin">Noye's Max. p. 33. F. N. B. 59. c. 16 E. 3. Tit. Waſt 100.2 E. 2. Waſt 1.</note> by <hi>Elegit,</hi> Statute-Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant or the Staple, but an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Account after the Debt and Dammages levied.</p>
               <p>Neither doth it lie againſt Tenant at Will; but if ſuch <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 57. a. 21 H. 6.38. 48 E. 3. f. 25. 11 H. 6. f. 38. 12 E. 4. f. 8.22 E. 4.5.21 H. 6. f. 43. Kitchin, f. 237. a. b. Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave &amp; Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet's ca. Mich. 29 &amp; 30 El. Goldsb. Rep. p. 72. pl. 17.</note> Tenant voluntarily pull down the Houſes or cut down Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-trees, &amp;c. in this caſe the Lord may have an Action of Treſpaſs againſt him, <hi>Quare vi &amp; armis,</hi> &amp;c. but for permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:60010:82"/>
Waſte the Lord hath no Remedie againſt him.</p>
               <p>Either Waſte or Account will lie againſt Tenant in Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, <note place="margin">Noye's Max. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> for he hath Fee Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional.</p>
               <p>There are 5 ſeveral Writs of Waſte; 2 at the Common <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 54. a.</note> Law, for Waſte done by Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in Dower or the Guardian; and 3 by the Statute-Law, for Waſte done by Tenant for Life, for Years, and Tenant by the Courteſie.</p>
               <p>If two or more Joint-tenants <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 200. b. Reg. 163. f. N. B. 127. &amp; 1 part Inſt. f. 54. b.</note> or Tenants in common be of a Houſe of Habitation, and the one of them will not repair the Houſe, the other in that caſe may have a Writ <hi>De reparatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne facienda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Leſſor covenant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair <note place="margin">12 H. 8. f. 1. Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 54. b. Vid. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 54.</note> the Houſe, and doth not, in this caſe the Leſſee may cut Timber growing upon the ground and repair it, though
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:60010:82"/>
he be not compellable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and ſhall not be puniſhed in Waſte for cutting the Wood.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe of an <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Houſe and Lands, without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of Waſte for the Houſe, yet may the Leſſee not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding repair the Houſe with the Timber growing upon the ground, though he may ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly waſte the Houſe if he will.</p>
               <p>No perſon ſhall have an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 53. b. F. N. B. 59. f. 8 R. 2. Waſt 47.27 H. 8.13.</note> of Waſte, unleſs he hath the immediate ſtate of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; but ſometime another ſhall joyn with him for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; as if a Reverſion be granted to two and the Heirs of the one, they two ſhall joyn in an Action of Waſte.</p>
               <p>And in like ſort the ſurvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> Coparcener and the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant by the Courteſie ſhall joyn in an Action of Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Eſtate-Tail deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 2 H. 4.22.</note>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:60010:83"/>
hanging the Action of Waſte, and the Plaintiff become Tenant in Tail after poſſibility of Iſſue extinct, the Action of Waſte is gone.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant do Waſte, and <note place="margin">2 H. 4. Co. <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</hi> Noye's Max. p. 33.</note> he in the Reverſion dieth, the Heir ſhall not have an Action of Waſte for the Waſte done in the life of the Anceſtor.</p>
               <p>Nor a Biſhop, Maſter of an <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Hoſpital, Parſon, &amp;c. in the time of the Predeceſſor.</p>
               <p>If Leſſee for Years commit Waſte and die, no Action of <note place="margin">Idem ibidem. 10 E. 4.1.49 E. 3. 25. 11 E. 2. Wa. 115. 2 Mar. 117. 8 E. 2. Waſte 110.</note> Waſte lieth againſt his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Adminiſtrators for Waſte done before their time.</p>
               <p>If two Coparceners be of a <note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> Reverſion, and the one of them dies, the Aunt and Niece ſhall join in an Action of Waſte.</p>
               <p>If Lands be given two, and <note place="margin">C. 1 par. Inſt f. 53. b. &amp; 200. b. 24 E. 3. 27. 50 E. 3.3.8 H. 6. 13. Co. 2 part Inſt. on Stat. Glou. ch. 5.</note> the heirs of one of them, he that hath the Fee ſhall not have an Action of Waſte upon the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:60010:83"/>
Statute of <hi>Glouc.</hi> for that they are Joynt-tenants; but his Heir ſhall have an Action of Waſte againſt Tenant for Life.</p>
               <p>If Leſſee for Life commit <note place="margin">F. N. B. 36. b. 14 H 8. f. 11. Kitchin, f. 244. a. b.</note> Waſte, and after ſurrender his Eſtate, and the Leſſor accepts it; now the Leſſee is diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the Waſte.</p>
               <p>If a Stranger make Waſte <note place="margin">Kitchin, ibid. 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. f. 3. 3 H. 6. f. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. b.</note> upon the Lands which one holdeth for Life or Years, the Termor ſhall be puniſhed for it, and is left to take his Remedy over.</p>
               <p>But if the Leſſor himſelf <note place="margin">Kitchin, <hi>ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prá.</hi> 5 H. 4. f. 3.</note> make Waſte, the Tenant ſhall not ſuffer for that Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Tenant make Waſte <note place="margin">Idem ibid. 48 E. 3. f. 15. 34 H. 6. f. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> before his Attornment, he ſhall not be liable to an Action for it.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor covenant to deliver Timber out of the ſame <note place="margin">44 E. 3. f. 21. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Land to repair the Houſe let,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:60010:84"/>
and will not, and for lack there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Leſſee will not repair it, but ſuffers the Houſe to fall; in this caſe he is puniſhable for ſuch Waſte: But if the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <note place="margin">Idem ibid.</note> be to be taken out of other Lands, and is not delivered, then the Tenant is excuſable if he ſuffer the Houſe to fall, and no Action of Waſte lies againſt him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> After the Waſte <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 53. b.</note> done, there is a ſpecial regard to be had to the continuance of the Reverſion in the ſame eſtate that it was at the time of the Waſte done; for if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Waſte he grant it over, though he take back the whole Eſtate again, yet is the Waſte diſpuniſhable: and ſo it is if he grant the Reverſion to the uſe of himſelf and his Wife, and of his Heirs, yet the Waſte is diſpuniſhable, and ſo of the like; becauſe the Eſtate of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:60010:84"/>
the Reverſion continues not, but is altered, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Action of Waſte for Waſte done before (which conſiſteth in privity) is gone.</p>
               <p>A Prohibition of Waſte did lie againſt Tenant by the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, <note place="margin">Bract. l. 4. f. 315, 316. Brit. f. 168. Dr. &amp; Stud. l. 2. ch. 1. 12 H. 4.3. 10 H. 3. Waſt 142. 4 H. 3. Waſt 140. Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Tenant in Dower, and Guardian in Chivalry by the Common Law, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tenant for Life or Years, becauſe they came in by the Leſſor's own Act, and he might have provided that no Waſte ſhould be done.</p>
               <p>Tenant by the Courteſie or <note place="margin">Noye's Max. p. 33. Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> F. N. B. 56. e. f. and ſee Co. 3. l. in Walker's ca. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. in Beaumont's ca. Regeſt. 72.</note> in Dower can hold of none but the Heir and his Heir by deſcent; and therefore if they grant over their Eſtate, and the Grantee doth Waſte, yet the Action muſt be brought againſt themſelves for the Waſte done, and not againſt the Aſſigns or Grantees.</p>
               <p>But if the Heir either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:60010:85"/>
the Aſſignment had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or after the Aſſignment doth grant the Reverſion over; in both theſe caſes the Grantee muſt bring the Action of Waſte againſt the Aſſignee, for now the privity is deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>In all other Caſes the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Waſte muſt be brought <note place="margin">Co. 1 par. Inſt. f. 54. a. 27 E. 4.81. 26 E. 5. Waſte 10.</note> againſt the parties that commit the Waſte, (for it is in nature of a Treſpaſs) unleſs it be in caſe of a Ward; for there if the Guardian doth Waſte and aſſign over, the Action lieth againſt the Aſſignee.</p>
               <p>A Guardian ſhall not be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 12 H. 4.3. 3 E. 3. Waſt 146. Fleta, l. 1. ch. 11.</note> for Waſte done by a Stranger.</p>
               <p>But Tenant by the Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <note place="margin">Idem ibid. F. N. B<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 59. a. &amp; 60. g. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> in Dower, for Life, Years, &amp;c. ſhall be puniſhed for VVaſte done by a Stranger, and are left to take their Remedy over againſt the Stranger as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:60010:85"/>
If VVaſte be made by <note place="margin">F. N. B. 59. l. Kitchin, f. 244. b.</note> ſtrange Enemies or ſudden Tempeſt, the Termor is diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable for ſuch VVaſte. See before ch. 11. p. 127.</p>
               <p>If Land be let to a Feme <note place="margin">F. N. B. 36. b. 3 E. 3. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 20. Kitchin <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> ſole, and ſhe take Husband, who commits VVaſte and dies; ſhe ſhall be puniſhed for this VVaſte.</p>
               <p>But if the Leaſe were made <note place="margin">Kitchin, ibid. Finch, l. 1. ch. 3. p. 26.</note> to the Husband and Wife, and he commits VVaſte and dies; in this caſe ſhe ſhall not be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for ſuch VVaſte, unleſs ſhe agree to the Eſtate.</p>
               <p>If there be two Joynt-te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of a VVard, and one of <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 54. a. 33 E. 3. Waſt 6.</note> them commit VVaſte, both ſhall anſwer for it.</p>
               <p>An Infant and Baron and Feme ſhall be puniſhed for <note place="margin">Co. ibid. Vide 15 H. 3. Waſte 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> VVaſte done by a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>If a Feme Tenant for Life <note place="margin">Co. ibid. Vide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on's caſe, 35 El. Co. 5. l. f. 73. 49 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3.25.46 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. Waſte Statham. 10 H. 6.11, 12.</note>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:60010:86"/>
take Husband, and the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band doth VVaſte, and the VVife dieth; in this caſe he is not puniſhable for ſuch VVaſte: but if a Feme be poſſeſſed of a Term of years, and take Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band who commits VVaſte, and the VVife dies; here he ſhall be liable to an Action of VVaſte for the VVaſte by him commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe the Law giveth the Term to him.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for Life grant over <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 30 E. 3.10.</note> his Eſtate upon Condition, and the Grantee doth VVaſte, and the Grantor re-entereth for the Condition broken; the Action of VVaſte ſhall be brought againſt the Grantee, and the place waſted recovered.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, <note place="margin">Co. Ibid. 48 E. 3. 19.</note> and VVaſte is done, and the Lord entereth; in this caſe the Lord ſhall not be puniſhed for VVaſte done before En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but for VVaſte after he ſhall.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:60010:86"/>
An Occupant ſhall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <note place="margin">Co. ibid. &amp; vide Co. 6. l. f. 37. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Dean and Chap. de Worc. caſe; &amp; l. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. f 9. b. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 53.</note> for Waſte; and ſo if an Eſtate be made to <hi>A</hi> and his Heirs during the Life of <hi>B,</hi> and <hi>A</hi> dies, his Heir ſhall be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in Waſte.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to <hi>A</hi> for <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 54. a. 50 E. 3. 3. 4 E. 3. 18. Perkins, 619. F. N. B. 58. c. &amp; 59. h. 33 E. 3. Waſt 144. 11 E. 3. Receit 118. 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. 9 Regeſt. 74. Paget &amp; Carie's caſe vouched in Co. 2. lib. in Bingham's ca. f. 92. &amp; Co. 5. l. f. 76. Page<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> caſe there, 35 El. in C. B.</note> Life, the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>B</hi> for Life, the Remainder to <hi>C</hi> in F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; in this caſe if <hi>A</hi> make Waſte, no Action lieth againſt him du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Life of <hi>B;</hi> but if <hi>B</hi> die, then an Action of VVaſte lies againſt <hi>A</hi> for the VVaſte done in the Life of <hi>B;</hi> becauſe it was <hi>ad exhaereditationem</hi> of him in Remainder in Fee, and now the impediment (which was the mean Eſtate for Life) is taken away.</p>
               <p>And where it is ſaid in ſome <note place="margin">Vide Paget's ca. <hi>ubi ſuprá,</hi> in Co. 5. l. Herne's Law of Conv. p. 53.</note> Books, that he in Remainder or Reverſion in Fee ſhall not have an Action of VVaſte, it
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:60010:87"/>
is to be intended during the continuance of the mean Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder for Life: again, where it is ſaid in ſome other Books, that an Action of Waſte doth lie, it is meant after the death of him in Remainder for Life, &amp; not otherwiſe, therefore <hi>nota.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a Leaſe for Life be made, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inch, l. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h. 3. p <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Co. 1 part I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. f. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Vide Herne's Law of Conv. p. 50, &amp; 53.</note> the Remainder for Years, the Remainder in Fee; here an Action of VVaſte lies pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently againſt the Tenant for Life, during the term in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, for this mean term for years is no impediment.</p>
               <p>But if a man maketh a Leaſe for Life or Years, and after <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá;</hi> &amp; Vide 4 F. 3. 18.</note> granteth the Reverſion for Years, the Leſſor ſhall have no Action of Waſte during the years; for he himſelf hath granted away the Reverſion in reſpect whereof he is to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Action: but it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if he had made a Leaſe in
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:60010:87"/>
Reverſion, which had been but a future Intereſt, for there an Action of VVaſte lieth during the term, and the term ſhall be ſaved in that caſe.</p>
               <p>If an Action of VVaſte be brought, and pending the VVrit <note place="margin">11 H. 6. f. 8. F. N B. fo. 60.14 H. 8. f. 12. Kitchin, f. 246. b.</note> the term end, yet the VVrit ſhall not abate; for although the Plaintiff cannot recover the place waſted, yet he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the treble Dammages.</p>
               <p>And ſo where one that holds <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 285 a. 11 H. 6.43. 9 E. 4.50.</note> for term of another's Life makes VVaſte, and afterwards <hi>Ceſtui que vie</hi> dies; here the Leſſor ſhall recover Dammages, although he cannot recover the place waſted.</p>
               <p>If Tenant for Life or Years or their Aſſignes make a Grant <note place="margin">F. N. B. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. Kit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 36 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. in C. B. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he's caſe. Co. 5. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 77.</note> over, and yet take the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits; then an Action of VVaſte lieth againſt him by him in Reverſion or Remainder, by the Statute of 11. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:60010:88"/>
If Waſte be done in one <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 54. a. &amp; 2 part In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. fo. 304. 4 E. 6. Waſte 136. 18 H. 8. 1. 15 H. 7. 11. 8 E. 3. Waſte 112. 4 E. 2. 32. 15 E. 3. Waſte 108. See Temps E. 1. Waſt 122, and 134. Kitchin, f. 246. b. Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Practicale, p. 343. Herne's Law of Conveyances, p. 54.</note> Corner of a Wood, that onely ſhall be recovered; but if it be <hi>ſparſim,</hi> that is here and there in the Wood, then the whole Wood ſhall be recovered, or as much wherein the Waſte <hi>ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim</hi> is done.</p>
               <p>And ſo in Houſes, ſo many <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 54. a. 8 E. 2. Waſt 112.</note> Rooms ſhall be recovered wherein there is Waſte done; but if the Waſte be done <hi>ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim,</hi> through all, then all ſhall be recovered.</p>
               <p>If a man make a Leaſe for Life, and by Deed grant that if any Waſte be done, that it ſhall be redreſſed by Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and not by Suit or Plea; yet notwithſtanding an Action of Waſte doth lie, for the place waſted cannot be recovered without Plea.</p>
               <p>If a man make Waſte in <note place="margin">4 E 6. Waſt 136. per Bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ley. &amp; Paſch. 1650. in B. R. <hi>per</hi> Juſt. Jermy n. Vid. Regeſt pract. p. 343.</note>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:60010:88"/>
cutting Trees which grow in Hedg-rows which incloſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, nothing ſhall be recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but <hi>Locus vaſtatus,</hi> that is the Circuit of the Roots, and not the whole Paſture: But if the Trees grew <hi>ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Reg. pract. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> ſcatteringly about the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, then the whole Paſture is forfeited if they be cut.</p>
               <p>It is a good Plea in Bar to a Writ of Waſte, to ſay that the <note place="margin">43 E. 6. f. 6. Waſt Kitchin, f. 247. a.</note> Houſe fell by ſudden Tempeſt, although the Termor did co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to repair it; but it is no Plea in a Writ of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>It is a good Plea in Waſte to ſay, that at the time of the <note place="margin">Kitchin, <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 49 E. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 7. Waſt.</note> Leaſe made the Houſe was ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inous, and the Timber putre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and rotten, ſo that it fell; for if any of the principal Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber were rotten, it is no Waſte, though he did covenant to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair it. See before, ch. 2. p. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:60010:89"/>
It is alſo a good Plea to ſay, <note place="margin">8 H. 6. f. 27. Waſt. 8 H. 5. f. 8. Waſt, mes veies Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 285. a.</note> that the Plaintiff hath entred upon the Land, before which Entry no Waſte was made; or that he Surrendred, and the Plaintiff did accept, before which time no Waſte was made.</p>
               <p>It is no Plea to ſay, that at <note place="margin">19 H. 6. f. 66. Vide Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 283. a. &amp; Kitchin, f. 247. b.</note> the day of the Writ purchaſed the Houſe was ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired; but he muſt ſay after the Waſte committed, and before the Writ purchaſed, it was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently repaired; and this is a good Plea.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſee doth Waſte, <note place="margin">19 H. 6. 66. 14 H. 6. 14. 11 R. 2. Waſte 99. Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 285. a.</note> and after ſurrenders, and the Leſſor agrees; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Leſſor may have an Action of Waſte, and recover the treble Dammages.</p>
               <p>If an Action of Waſte be brought by Baron and Feme in <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi> 2 H. 4.22.6 F. 2. Brief. 807.</note> Remainder in ſpecial Tail, and pending the Writ the Wife di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:60010:89"/>
without Iſſue; now the Writ in this caſe ſhall abate, becauſe every kind of Action of Waſte muſt be <hi>ad exhaeredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If there be two Joynt-te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 200. b. Weſtm. 2 chap. 22. Vide Raſtall Waſte 6. Wingate's Abr. Stat. p. 552. Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer's <hi>Mag. Charta,</hi> fo. 71. b. Co. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> part Inſt. fo.</note> of a Wood, Turbary, Piſcary, or the like, and one of them doth Waſte againſt the will of the other; here the other may have an Action of Waſte againſt him, and he that did the Waſte hath election before Judgment either to take his part in certainty by the Sheriff and the Oath of 12 men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. or that he grant that from thenceforth he ſhall not doe Waſte, but according to his proportion, &amp;c. and if he make choice of a certain place, then the place waſted ſhall be aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him.</p>
               <p>And this doth extend as well <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. fo. 200. a. b. 47 E. 3. 22. b. 2 H. 5. 1, &amp; 3.</note>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:60010:90"/>
to Tenants in common and Joynt-tenants for Life, as to an Eſtate of Inheritance: but if one Tenant in common or Joynt-tenant out of a Dove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe deſtroy the whole Flight of Doves, no Action of Waſte doth lie in that caſe upon the Statute, but the other may have an Action of Treſpaſs againſt him that deſtroyed them, <hi>quare vi &amp; armis Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbare le Pl<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>. fregit, &amp;</hi> 200 <hi>Columbas Pret.</hi> 40 <hi>interfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>If a Leaſe be made to hold to one without any impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 220. a. Vide Co. Reports, l. 2. f. 23. l. 9. f. 9. l. 12. f. 83.</note> of Waſte, then the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee may cut down Trees, and convert them to his own uſe; but if the words be, to hold without impeachment for any Action of Waſte, then in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> caſe if the Leſſee cut dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Trees, the Leſſor ſhall hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, for the diſcharge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:60010:90"/>
but to the Action.</p>
               <p>If Leſſee for Life grant a <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 233. b. &amp; 234. a.</note> Rent-charge, and after doth Waſte, and the Leſſor recover in an Action of Waſte, he ſhall hold the Land charged during the Life of the Tenant for Life; but if the Rent were granted after the Waſte done, the Leſſor ſhall then avoid the Grant made by the Leſſee for Life.</p>
               <p>A Parſon, Vicar, Arch-dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, Prebend, &amp;c. may have <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 341. a. 10 H. 7. 5. F. N. B. 55. d. &amp; 57. c.</note> an Action of Waſte, and the Writ ſhall be ſaid <hi>ad exhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditationem Eccleſiae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> B, or, <hi>Praebendae ipſius</hi> A.</p>
               <p>If Tenant in Fee releaſe to his Tenant for Life all his <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 345. b. 42. F. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 23 F. N. B. 60. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 41 E. 3. Waſt 83. 42 E. 3. 18.</note> Right, yet he ſhall have an Action of Waſte.</p>
               <p>And if Tenant in Tail make a Leaſe for his own Life, yet <note place="margin">Idem Ibid.</note> he ſhall have an Action of Waſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:60010:91"/>
But if Tenant for Life be, the Remainder to another in <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 345. b. 43 Aſſ. pl. 13.41 E. 3. Waſt 83.11 H. 4.67.13 H. 7.10. Plo. Com. 482.</note> Tail, and he in the Remainder releaſe to the Tenant for Life all his Right and State in the Land; in this caſe he cannot afterwards have an Action of Waſte.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſor bring an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 356. a. 46 E. 3. 20. 8 H. 6.13.30 H. 6. 7.</note> of Waſte againſt his Leſſee, the Leſſee cannot plead gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally <hi>Riens en le Reverſion,</hi> but he muſt ſhew how and by what means the Reverſion is deveſted out of him.</p>
               <p>But if the Grantee of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion bring an Action of <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> Waſte, the Leſſee may plead generally, that he hath nothing in the Reverſion.</p>
               <p>If a Biſhop make a Leaſe <note place="margin">Co. 1 part Inſt. f. 356.</note> for Life or Years and dies, and the Leſſee, the See being void, doth Waſte; in this caſe the Succeſſor ſhall have an Action of Waſte,</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:60010:91"/>
And ſo if Leſſee for Life be diſſeiſed, and Waſte is done, <note place="margin">Co. <hi>ubi ſuprá.</hi>
                  </note> and the Leſſee re-enters; here an Action of Waſte lieth againſt him.</p>
               <p>If Leſſor and Leſſee for Years, &amp;c. join in the cutting <note place="margin">Mich. 18 H. 8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Perkins, 202.</note> down of 20 Oaks, &amp;c. grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Lands leaſed, the Leſſor ſhall not puniſh the Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee for the ſame.</p>
               <p>If the Leſſee before his term begin enter into the Lands let to him, and doe an Act which amounteth unto Waſte, the Leſſor ſhall not have an Action of Waſte for the ſame.</p>
               <p>None ſhall have Judgment to <note place="margin">Finch, l. 1. ch. 3. p. 29.</note> recover in an Action of Waſte, where the Waſte comes but to 12<hi rend="sup">d</hi> or ſuch a petty Summe; for <hi>De minimis non curat Lex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Waſte be done upon <note place="margin">Co. 2 part Inſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 303. Regeſ. Prac. p. 343.</note> Lands let for term of Years or Life, by one againſt whom the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:60010:92"/>
Leſſee can have no Remedy in Law for committing the ſame Waſte; the Leſſee in ſuch caſe is not puniſhable for the ſame by the Leſſor, except there be a ſpecial Covenant in the Leaſe, that he ſhall not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit nor ſuffer Waſte to be done.</p>
               <p>Note well, what hath been here ſaid concerning Guardians in Chivalry and their Wards, is but onely to ſhew what the Law was formerly in thoſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: for now by the Stat. of 12 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. chap. 24. Wardſhip (that former undoing of many Gentlemen) Primer-Seiſins, and all <hi>Ouſter le mains,</hi> &amp;c. are quite taken away, and all hold now in free and common Soccage; and every Father, whether he be at age of 21 years or under, may by Deed executed in his life-time, or by his laſt Will and Teſtament in
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:60010:92"/>
writing, in the preſence of two or more credible Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes delivered, diſpoſe of his Children under the age of 21 years, and not married at the time of his Death, for and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuch time as they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main under the age of 21 years, or any leſſer time, to the Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Tuition of any perſon or perſons in Poſſeſſion or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder, (Popiſh Recuſants ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted:) and ſuch Diſpoſition of ſuch Child or Children ſince the 24 <hi>Febr.</hi> 1645, or hereafter to be made, ſhall be good againſt all and every perſon and perſons claiming ſuch Child or Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as Guardian in Soccage, or otherwiſe, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:60010:93"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>An Abridgment of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the</hi> 43 Elizab. <hi>and the</hi> 15 <hi>of</hi> Car. 2. <hi>about the unlawful cutting, ſtealing or ſpoiling of Wood, &amp;c. neceſſary for all Gentlemen to know.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF any ſhall be convicted by his own Confeſſion, or by the Teſtimony of one Witneſs upon Oath, before one Juſtice of Peace, or Head-Officer, to have unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cut or taken away any Grain growing, robbed any Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard or Garden, digged up or taken away any Fruit-Trees, broken any Hedges, Pales, or other Fences, cut or ſpoiled any Woods or Under-woods, ſtanding and growing, or the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:60010:93"/>
like, or to have been acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thereunto, he ſhall, within ſuch time as the Juſtice or Head-Officer ſhall appoint, pay for the firſt Offence to the party grieved ſo much as the Juſtice or Head-Officer ſhall ſet down: and in caſe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty offending be not able to pay it, or do it not according to Order, then the Offender is by them or either of them (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively) to be committed to the Conſtable, or other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the Place where the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence was committed, or the party apprehended to be whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped; and ſo for every Offence afterwards, and proved as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, the Offender is to have the like puniſhment of Whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</p>
               <p>If the Conſtable refuſe or neglect to whip the Offender, any ſuch Juſtice of Peace or Head-Officer may commit him
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:60010:94"/>
to Priſon without Bail, till he whip or cauſe to be whipped the party offending, as is above declared.</p>
               <p>No Juſtice may execute this Statute for Offences done to himſelf, unleſs he be aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with one or more Juſtices of Peace whom the Offence doth not concern. <hi>Stat.</hi> 43. <hi>El. ch.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>Statute</hi> of the 15. <hi>Car.</hi> 2. is an Additional Act to this, as follows.</p>
               <p>That every Conſtable, Head-borough, or other perſon in every County, City, Town Corporate, or other place where they ſhall be Officers or Inhabitants, ſhall have power to apprehend or cauſe to be apprehended ſuch as they ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect for having, or carrying, or any waies conveying any Burthen or Bundles of any
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:60010:94"/>
kinde of Wood, Under-wood, Poles, or young Trees, Bark or Baſt of Trees, or any Gates, Styles, Poſts, Pales, Rails, or Hedg-wood, Broom, or Furze.</p>
               <p>If any perſon be ſuſpected to have any ſuch Woods, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-woods, &amp;c. any Officer, by Warrant under the hand and Seal of one Juſtice, may enter by virtue thereof in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Houſes, Out-houſes, Yards, Gardens, or other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces belonging to ſuch perſons, and whereſoever they finde any ſuch, they may apprehend thoſe perſons, and alſo thoſe who are ſuſpected to have cut and taken the ſame, and carry them before a Juſtice of the Peace of the County, City, &amp;c. and if he in whoſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody ſuch Wood, &amp;c. is found, cannot give a good Account, which may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:60010:95"/>
to the Juſtice, how he came by the ſame with the conſent of the Owner, or do not within a convenient time, ſet down by the Juſtice, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the party of whom he bought the ſame Wood, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-wood, &amp;c. or ſome other credible Witneſs to depoſe upon Oath ſuch Sale of the ſaid Wood, Under-wood, &amp;c. (which the Juſtice may admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter:) that then the ſaid per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall be deemed convict of the ſaid offence of cutting and ſpoiling of the ſame Woods, Under-woods, &amp;c. within the meaning of the before-recited Statute of the 43. of <hi>Eliz.</hi> and be liable to the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein contained; and to pay over and above down preſently, to the uſe of the Overſeers of the Poor of the place where the Offence is committed, for the Firſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:60010:95"/>
ſuch a ſumme, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding 10<hi rend="sup">s</hi>, as the Juſtice ſhall appoint. And if the Offender ſhall not perform the Juſtice's Order herein to the Owner, and alſo to the Overſeers of the Poor, then the Juſtice is to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to the Houſe of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, for ſo long (not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding one Moneth) as he ſhall think meet, or to be whipt by the Conſtable or other Officer, as the Juſtice ſhall judge moſt expedient. And if ſuch perſon ſhall again offend in the like kinde, and be convicted as before, then he muſt be ſent to the Houſe of Correction for one Moneth, and be there held to hard Labour. And if he do offend the third time, and be convicted as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, then he ſhall be taken, adjudged, and deemed as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible Rogue.</p>
               <p>If any buy any Burthens of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:60010:96"/>
Wood, &amp;c. (as before named) which may be juſtly ſuſpected to have been ſtoln or unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come by; any Juſtice, Mayor, Bailiff, or Head-Officer within his Juriſdiction, may, upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to him made, examine the matter upon Oath, which they may adminiſter: and if he find that the ſame was bought of one that may be juſtly ſuſpected to have ſtoln or unlawfully come by the ſame, he may then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the party that bought the ſame, to pay Treble the value to the party from whom they were ſtoln or unlawfully come by, and in default of preſent payment thereof, iſſue out his Warrant to levy the ſame by Diſtreſs and Sale of the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's goods, rendring the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus to the owner of ſuch goods; and for lack of ſuch diſtreſs, to commit the party to the Gaol, there to remain
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:60010:96"/>
without Bail for the ſpace of one Moneth at his own charges.</p>
               <p>Note, that no man is to be puniſhed by this Law, that hath been puniſhed by a former Law for the ſame Offence: nor is any man to be queſtioned for any offence in this Statute, unleſs he be queſtioned for the ſame within ſix weeks after the Offence is committed.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
